Those whose hearts are troubled, all who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship
him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st
Enoch, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as a true
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God,
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening.
giant killers, dragon slayers, scorpion stompers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spears podcast.
My co-host father, Stephen D. Young, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm father, Andrew Stephen Damick.
You know, Mayan's Pennsylvania.
Tonight, we're not taking any calls because this is a pre-recorded episode.
Unless you happen to call in while we're recording.
Yeah, which, hey, call us.
See, it's not working.
In this does air live, though, Father Stephen will be in Canada.
something like that, which honestly sounds to me like the best place to be in July. Definitely not Phoenix.
I've done a lot of driving though on the roads of America.
So far visiting 44 out of our 50 states. Probably my favorite highway road signs I've seen out there are
the ones that read, prepare to meet Vardume. And it's not just because of the lovely early modern
English pronoun. I promise you. This is the next installment.
in our eschatology series.
And it's doom we're talking about.
The final judgment, Doomsday itself.
What exactly is this?
Is the end of days about everyone going to heaven or hell?
Or is it just a Schwarzenegger action horror flick?
What do you think, father?
Well, it's not just a Schwarzenegger action horror flick.
I mean, it is that with Gabriel Burns, the devil.
Amazing.
Again, I say amazing.
Gabriel Burns. It is great. It is great. Spiritual warfare with a grenade launcher. I tell I always do that.
So that's, yeah, that's grooming. But I mean, when I first started trying to put together notes,
you know, episode title, Doomsday, I'm typing out, you know, Doomsday is a Kryptonian bioweapon that
It was made to evolve upon its death and regenerate that killed Superman.
that you corrected me.
I was like, oh, bummer.
There's also the Legion of Doom.
Yeah.
Dr. Doom.
Dr. Von Doom.
Doom.
Simply Doom.
We all remember that game.
Yes.
Tholsa Doom has played in Conan, the Barbarian, by my nemesis, James Earl Jones.
That's a good one. How's
that going? I'm I'm I'll think
it's not as great don't worry.
There's a professional wrestling
tag team named Doom featuring
Ron Simmons and Butcheried.
Well yeah that was a long time ago.
We did a dude was the other name
for the road warriors also.
it was a
survived the Legion of Doom 2000.
Anyway, we digress as much as people love our digression.
There is a doctor doom that either heads up
or is associated with the eighth day institute
out in Kansas.
Actually, that's just his real name, so Disney can't sue him.
That is his real name.
He's actually named Doom, his last name is Doom
and he has a doctorate of some kind.
I don't know where it is, but.
Yeah.
Yeah, he didn't go to seven years of medical school that we called Mr. Doom, right?
So yeah, no, we're talking about the end of days, the end of the world, the day of judgment.
And so you use the phrase end of days, not primarily so that we can bring up the Arnold
short-sending movie because I don't think you've actually
seen it. I have not, which is a huge hole, a doom sized hole, is it where?
In your cultural knowledge. I saw it in the theater twice, not once but twice.
In the same week. I think it was different weeks.
Okay, well, all right. Yeah. But I think I got a video. That was it wasn't that
later.
stage of the Arnold Schwarzenegger action career, right? It was around the time of like the
sixth day, which despite the title does not really have a biblical theme.
It's a point.
No, he just gets cloned in it and has to fight himself.
Just before he started doing all those just silly comedy things.
Right. Then he went into comedy. He's had a late career renaissance that a lot of people
have been aware of because some of the way he made a movie called Aftermath that is sort of the
antithesis of his movies. It's like repentance for his his former life as a film star.
So his his retractions as it were like like like a guzzin or a coinus. It's about the consequences of
violence. Good for him. There's a little bit of more of a realistic take. I mean if I were a
or a governor of California, I would have a lot of repentance to engage in myself.
you know, it was him or Gary Coleman.
So there's my
we
the end of the end of days.
That phrase end of days,
which already picked up for that movie's title,
is a phrase that starts being used in second temple Jewish
literature.
and it's still used.
in a lot of Jewish circles to refer to the last day, the day of judgment.
Even though that phrase does not appear in and of itself, end of days, right?
That exact phrase does not occur anywhere in the Hebrew Bible or the Christian Bible.
And it is miblically derived, right?
And the con...
concept is even kind of reference in the New Testament.
So I mean, the most obvious biblical derivation is that Genesis 1
in describing the creation of the world,
we have the separation of light from darkness and then day 1.
Right?
You have a progression of days.
Yeah.
And after Noah's flood, when the promise is made,
and the rainbow is given as a sign of it.
that sets down his bow, like bow and arrow in the clouds.
And promises that the various cycles,
right day and night, springtime and harvest,
the flow of the days and seasons and times and years
will continue until the end.
So there you have, there's going to be days.
There's going to be a regular succession of days
until those days end, right?
So you can see end of days can...
naturally from. There's a beginning there's going to be an end from that idea, right? And of course,
it's sort of implied by the language of the last days, right? In these last days, which
gets picked up by several biblical authors, just a couple of examples out of many possible ones.
Hebrews 1, verse 2, James 5, verse 3. The idea that these are the last days implies, obviously,
that there's going to be an end of days.
which is approaching, right?
And that you are in the final days,
you are in that last period.
Which is kind of funny because,
like, especially since,
particularly I think since the 1970s,
where you get how Lindsey and some of these guys
kind of saying these are the last days.
But it's like, well,
we've, they were saying it was these last days
back in the New Testament, you know?
So because as we...
talked about ages the last episode right we're in the last one yeah until before the end of the age right
yeah yeah and um we're we're in such a Christian context in our thought
that this doesn't strike us as weird.
the idea that the world's going to have an end.
Yeah.
Right.
But if you go back to the rest of the ancient world right outside of Israel, in general,
right, I mean, people have heard of Ragnarok.
It's that right, the twilight and the gods and all this.
Yeah.
But most nations didn't actually have that.
No.
Yeah.
Yeah, there's the...
most over or not don't have a story about their gods all dying in the world ending.
Yeah. It was, in fact, they believed the world had kind of always been here and it kind of
always would. There were just these cycles that would repeat, right? And we've talked before,
in terms of the gods that they worshiped, we've talked before about the succession myth.
And so those cycles included the succession of gods.
Right?
Yeah, Zeus may not be the highest God forever.
Someone could displace him in the future.
Right?
This has happened in the past.
Yeah, this has happened in the past.
We just move on, right?
You could have it, right?
Every generation, you get a new flash.
You get a new green lantern.
So this can just keep happening in perpetuity forever.
And all this has happened before, and all this will happen again.
Right?
But this gets transformed, right?
And we can see that in the Hebrew Scriptures that,
no, there is going to be an end.
There was a beginning and there will be an end.
Yeah, in a real sense, history is a biblical creation.
Right.
The idea of history as having some kind of trajectory,
having some kind of arc.
Yeah.
Yeah, right. Being some kind of
I know I'm playing out of things.
Yeah, I mean, there are certainly people
who recorded events that happened, right?
Without that concept, but they were just recording events
that happened.
Herodotus doesn't say like,
Herodotus certainly thought there were things
you could learn from things that had happened, right?
There was sort of wisdom or lessons to be derived from it.
But he didn't think that the Persian wars were part of this story.
We're sort of an act of a play that had started somewhere
and was leading somewhere in particular.
In fact, the way he understood meaning in history was based on the idea that
this is just cyclical and is all going to come around again.
So next time it comes around, right?
like you're the things we can learn from what happened last time, right?
So yeah, so this idea of a through line was a new thing and is different than what has typically
been considered. And ultimately even modern science, of course, the big bang is an idea
that a Catholic priest came up with, literally.
That's because he was trying to prove that the universe had a beginning.
For exactly this reason.
Even that, the idea of the big bang of the big crunch or the idea, right?
Doesn't get away from this, right?
It hasn't actually gone back to paganism.
Right.
And even your most die hard evolutionary theorist, if you watch any of these documentaries where
to try to like,
create the prehistoric world or whatever, they're presenting it as a story. They're presenting
it as sort of this narrative of life on Earth that started somewhere it is going to culminate
in humanity which in and of itself kind of makes no sense from their own perspective, from
their own atheistic perspective, right? Like why would humanity be any different?
Why is that the culmination of the story?
Why is it a story at all?
Why is it just a series of random events?
Why is there any kind of through line superimposed on it?
But so the reason why that's important
is that in order to understand judgment,
like the last one,
the way.
judgment, we have to obviously talk about justice. And the concept of justice
biblically is completely inseparable from the idea of order. I mean, that's simply what it is.
That Mishpah in Hebrew
justice is the state of everything being in its proper place and functioning.
the way it's meant to, right?
Everything is correctly related to everything else.
So that whether you're talking about society,
like human society, whether you're talking about nature,
whether you're talking about sort of the cosmos
as a whole, whether you're talking about
the angelic world, it doesn't matter, right?
Everything is in its proper place
and everything is functioning properly.
And of course,
In order for that to be true, right, in order there for there to be an order, in order
there to be any meaningful concept of justice in the world understood as a proper order,
that implies that there has to be some kind of order to creation which could be reflected
in that or not reflected in that, right?
What do I mean by that?
If...
the world really had no beginning and no end.
So let's take Aristotle's presuppositions say.
Then any particular say ordering of society
would be an ordering of society,
but how could you say whether it was just or unjust?
Like from what perspective?
Now you can, a variety of perspectives are possible.
You could say, well, I think the best ordering of society is one in which the people who are
lowest, you know, who are at the low end of the society are as high as possible.
So you can't really fall that low.
person could say well no I think the the right order
society is the one that gives people the most opportunities, whether they successfully take
advantage of them or not.
Another person could say, I think the best ordering of society is one that produces the
most human flourishing.
Another person could say, I think the best ordering of society is the one that allows great
men and women to be great, right, and to dominate the society and doesn't let the weak take
control of the mechanisms of power.
And you can jump.
than any given ordering, social ordering, from that perspective to say, well, this is good
from that perspective and this is bad from that perspective. But there's no way to mediate
between those perspectives. There's no way to say, no, this is the correct way to evaluate
a social order. Because every one of them is accidental. And so it's just going to be the person's
interest. So the
The idea that there is some kind of objective justice, that something can truly be just
or unjust in an objective way, that we could all come to agree upon, implies that there
is some kind of order, some kind of existing order, with which that societal ordering has
to be consonant has to correctly relate itself.
that this way of people relating to each other is correct.
Yeah, this is the basic idea behind, although not necessarily
work out in the details of the concept of natural law.
Sort of.
Yeah, that's one of the things for I first.
Yeah, yeah, that's the basis.
That could be grounded in different things.
Yeah.
It could be built into the nature of things in and of themselves.
It can be built into the laws of logic.
it can be God.
right? Right. Right. You could ground that different ways, but it has to be grounded somewhere.
Or you can't really have a meaningful concept of justice and injustice in any kind of object.
Yeah. Something absolute that everyone has to be obedient to, not that I just all agree on.
Right. Right. So what we see, as we've talked about many times of the show, in
and we
account of God's creation of the world is we've talked about two steps but the first step
and one of the key steps in creation is putting things in order. So God's act of creation
in ordering things and putting things in order entails automatically a concept of justice.
Right, that his ordering of things.
Right? Then constitutes once he pronounces it good and beautiful at the end of each day, right?
That his ordering of things is the ordering of things, right? Is the just ordering of things?
And any deviation from that then represents injustice. Yeah.
And when we look at descriptions of the last judgment, I know we've talked about just justice and
and judgment in general before.
on the show, but particularly with what we're talking about tonight with the last judgment,
the final judgment.
We have to understand a particular aspect of this in order to understand some of the language
that's used in talking about the last judgment.
And that's related to, again, this understanding of creation.
So the two steps that we talked about before, God puts things in order.
as on the first three days of creation. Then on the second set of three days, he fills
he fills things with life. Yeah, and then he gives that command to Adam and Eve to basically go
that go down do likewise essentially. Right. Right. To continue that. Right. And so there is this sort of
perfect perfect balance. Right. That's reflected in the image of a garden.
a garden is both order
and an order that produces and fosters life.
And so you can divert from that in one of two directions.
You can divert from that away from life.
Like Livey's famous quote about the Roman Empire,
they created a wasteland and called it peace.
You could expunge all the life.
You could have a very orderly parking lot.
a lot, right?
But there's no life there. On the other side, right, you can abandon order.
And while that can be seen as letting life take over, right, you abandon a building,
you abandon a town, and it becomes overgrown, right? You can see that as, oh, well, life has come
back in, right? Life has come and thrived there, right? But that kind of...
Disordered abundance of life, of biological life
actually becomes very dangerous
and very quickly can turn into death.
So, you know, for example, if I decide to go swimming
in my local Bayou here in Southern Louisiana,
especially if I'm skinny dipping,
things will not go well for me.
But it's nature, it's beautiful.
Yes.
I may avoid the gators.
avoid the snakes, I probably will not be able to avoid the mosquitoes for sure. And that
will give me who knows what. And not to mention everything else that's in the water, the
poisonous algae. But there's tons of life there. Yes, right. Right. But there's no order.
And so it becomes dangerous, right?
because it becomes chaos.
Right, it lapses back into chaos.
So, this is why we get certain metaphors
for the last judgment.
Some of them related to gardening,
directly, we're gonna talk about a couple of those.
But also why you get, and maybe especially
In the Hebrew prophets, you get description.
of judgment day that seem to involve a whole lot of people dying.
It sort of seem to involve depopulation.
And that language is being used there to counter this idea of
sort of overgrowing life turning into chaos.
But for a couple of those metaphors, we have a couple of metaphors from the gospels.
from Christ himself.
Yeah.
And the first one of these is sometimes called the parable of the weeds.
But I'm sure it's called 20 different things.
The wheat and the tears for all you King James.
Well, people love it.
There's another one that sometimes called the wheat and the tears.
That's true.
Yeah.
There's a lot of similar...
That's why we're going to read it here because there's a bunch of similar ones that we need to disambiguate.
we still use the word tear but it's probably because it's a homophonic.
that we kind of dropped it a long time ago.
I mean, maybe wheat farmers still do.
If any wheat farmers listening, send us an email.
Let us know.
You use the word tear.
In this way.
Yeah.
Okay.
So Matthew chapter 13, starting with verse 24,
he put another parable before them saying,
the kingdom of heaven may be compared to a man
who sowed good seed in his field.
But while his men were sleeping,
his enemy came and sowed weeds among the wheat
and went away.
So, when the plants came up and bore grain, then the weeds appeared also.
And the servants of the master of the house came and said to him, Master, Did you not so
good seed in your field?
How then does that have weeds?"
He said to them, And enemy has done this.
So the servants said to him, Then you want us to go and gather them?
But he said, No, lest in gathering the weeds you root up the wheat along with them.
Let both grow together until the harvest.
and at harvest time, I will tell the reapers,
gather the weeds first.
and bind them in bundles to be burned, but gather the wheat into my barn.
Right, so I mean, this is pretty directly that imagery, right, that this disorder, right,
comes into the otherwise orderly right fields of crops
that are ordered in order to
fourth life. And weeds, by the way, don't just like live peacefully alongside other plants.
Yeah, they're sucking the life out of them. Yes. They're actually harming the other plants.
But there's not this sort of immediate judgment. Right? There's not an immediate judgment. There's not
Okay.
The
...
second, there's there's this injustice immediately justice was we restored. Right.
Rather, right, this time is given, but then there comes a day. Eventually, there comes
a day when everything is harvested. And the reason for the delay is for the purpose of the
is for the purpose of the wheat.
Yeah, I mean there's some weeds, the
salvation of the wheat. There's some weeds if you pull them
you will kill everything around them.
Yeah.
Other weeds you can pull them out
and that's what you need to do, you know?
But in some cases, if you pull up the weeds,
then you're gonna ruin your actual good stuff.
Right.
And so this shows us what we might call
sort of the macrocosmic concept of judgment, right?
Because what Christ is clearly talking about here
is the day of judgment, the judgment of the whole world.
right, the separation of one type of person from another type of person to have different
fates.
Right.
But there's another type of judgment that he uses a not totally dissimilar example to describe.
Yeah, another good agricultural metaphor.
So John chapter 15 verses 1 and 2, I am the true vine and my father is the vine dresser.
branch in me that does not bear fruit he takes away.
And every branch that does bear fruit, he prunes that it may bear more fruit.
So this is the image of cutting off bits in order to make things better, rather than
weeding.
You know, this is pruning.
Now I've never...
You do have the element of branches being taken away.
Yeah, right?
That's part of it too, yeah, exactly.
You still have that, but there's also this other...
Other thing.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean I actually
very briefly had a grapevine. The grapes that made did not taste good, so we didn't keep
it. I heard it. They were grapes purely of wrath. But I do have some experience. I'm
not going to say I'm an expert or even a journeyman, but I do have experience pruning fruit
trees. We in my backyard, so I think I'd actually have about a third of an acre that my house
on and so the back end of it.
we have six fruit trees. And so over the last 10 years I've been planting trees
back there and pruning them because you have to prune them if you want good fruit
if you want the tree to do well fruit trees take a lot of work to make sure
that they thrive. And you know some of the basic principles are like if a branch
is kind of heading towards the middle of the tree you cut that one out. If it's
pointing.
downwards, you cut that. And you look and you see when it comes time for the fruit, you notice which
branches have fruit, and you privilege them. And the ones that don't do that, you take those off.
And so the idea is ultimately to try to, by privileging certain branches, then they get bigger and
bigger and bigger. Because fruit trees often like to just make a million little branches. But if you
take off a lot of the little ones that they put there and it puts their
energy into making some bigger branches. And then that can actually support the fruit when it
comes, because otherwise they can pull down the branches and break them off. So the general idea is
that by making some cutting, by removing some things, then it makes it stronger and healthier.
So there's a million sermons you could pre-tell that. I've probably one or two at my time,
but the idea, this is really pointing at repentance, is what's going on. God giving chastening,
God.
giving lessons that may not be super comfortable, but with the pruning then comes strength,
becomes better branches. And so this could be, we could describe this as sort of judgment
at the microcosm level, right? Like within a person. Yeah. Right. And this is what's being referred to
with, you know, if we judge ourselves, we will not be judged, right? The idea of putting the person
in order.
right, which at least in my case needs to happen repeatedly.
So, and that's why this has this ongoing nature of pruning,
right? It's not just like, okay, one time you go through and
straighten up the tree and, okay, now it's good forever.
Right. No, you have to, like I have to prune my trees two or
three times a year. You know, sometimes it doesn't work.
And there was one tree actually that I had one apple that for
years it was...
Like it was just a mess, but I kept going at it, kept going at it.
And finally now this year actually, it's got some height to it.
It's actually producing some apples.
So I mean, that's, you know, again, that's like human beings.
Sometimes it takes a long time if we're a lot of care, a lot of love,
before a person finally gets in order.
Yeah. And, and yeah.
And so not every judgment is just a complete
Cutting off.
Yeah, right.
Judgment is not all negative, right?
And even when it is kind of negative,
it's not all condemnation.
Yeah.
Right.
It's often aimed at correcting, disciplining, right?
Pruning here, right?
That's not completely cutting off the throw away.
And so we see sort of examples of that.
If you look at incidents.
of judgment, right, that we see, for example, in the Old Testament, right, so there's some obvious ones, right, Sodom and Gomorrah, right, clearly they get cut off, right, like that's, they get nuke for morbid, right.
they're gone, right? The giant clans, right? They reach a point they're cut off entirely, right?
So those, we could call them nations because Sodom and Gomorrah were city states with kings,
right?
Then the giant clans were clans.
Those nations are sort of cut off.
Well what about though Judah?
Judah gets taken into exile.
The first temple gets destroyed utterly.
land gets taken over by the Babylonians.
They're an exile for 70 years.
They get to come back, but there's still a Persian province.
Right?
They are an independent.
That's a nation that undergoes the other type of judgment.
Right?
The kind of corrective judgment.
There are certain practices of Judah that God is correcting.
Not all that different than the practices for which
she destroyed other nations by the way.
Right.
But as St. Paul says, speaking in part historically, God disciplines every son whom he loves, right? So due to gets corrected.
Right. And so, you know, we say that now we have this long reach of history. Right. Where we say, okay, well, yeah, that's corrective. That's corrective judgment. That's not like those other ones.
But if you were one of the people getting run through with a Babylonian sword,
in 587. Right.
If you were one of the ones getting deported to slavery,
if you were one of the ones watching everything burn,
if your children were being taken as slaves,
that didn't look all that different to you
on the ground than the other ones.
Right, so sometimes we let the distance of history
turn these things into statistics and numbers, right?
And so
So the judgment here, this is a real judgment.
It's not a different type of thing, right?
What's different tends to be the result, right?
The difference is the result.
And the result is usually a result of the people, but we'll talk about that more as we go
forward.
But with that in mind, how about
the northern kingdom of Israel. Yeah, they just thrown into the fire along with the
tears. Yeah, so on on on one level, right, you could say that. You could say, yeah, there's
this contrast between what happens to Israel, the northern kingdom and what happens to
Judah, the southern kingdom. And there are various reasons for that, right? The promises
is made to David, shoot as where the temple was, et cetera, et cetera.
Right?
No, we're keen.
Israel not so on those things. So you could say, well, okay, yeah, they get cut off and
Judah gets disciplined. But that's not really how, for example, St. Paul sees it. And St.
Paul didn't just come up with this. St. Paul is getting this from a lot of second temple
Jewish literature, like the Testaments of Naftali and stuff.
They already understood this this way. That saw what happened to Israel when they get dispersed
among the nations.
the northern kingdom as being not them being cut off and thrown into the fire, but them being
scattered like seeds, right? Like the fruit, the falls to the ground and dies, right?
And that the eventual inclusion of the nations who come to worship Israel's God,
which St. Paul, of course, believed was happening in his lifetime through his ministry, right?
And that gets prophesied in the Old Testament, so you don't have to look...
second type of Jewish literature for that.
Well, yeah, yeah.
But that is the harvest of the produce of those seeds.
Right?
And so when you look at it from this perspective of the result,
then what happens to the Northern Kingdom starts looking less like a total cutting off.
that it might at first blush before giving it more thought.
Well, those are all examples with nations, but you can find those same examples of those
two types, right, with individual people in the Old Testament.
Right.
So, just one example out of many, many, many, many possible examples, Saul, right, the
first king of Israel gets cut off ultimately.
Yep.
for his disobedience. And he doesn't get a lack of tries, right? He, it's, it's kind of
hard to discern when you're reading this all narrative, when exactly he was cut off
completely, right? There's not killing the amulakites. There's going to the witch of endor.
There's, right? There's a whole trying to murder David. I mean, there's a whole series of things.
Yeah. I mean, at a certain point, you do get that the Holy Spirit has left him and that there's
And I will speak.
here at the falls and around now.
Right.
But even then, right?
And part of the reason why it's hard to nail down
is, of course, he could have repented at any point
until he was dead.
Hmm.
Right?
So there wasn't actually a point of zero return.
Right.
But he adds up being cut off.
The way he dies is definitely a judgment.
and his household is mostly wiped out.
right? Um, whereas David, right? David faces judgment.
Nathan the prophet shows up to render judgment against David. Right?
Or actually, in that case, to turn David's own judgment around on him,
because David is king orders the man who did the horrible thing to be put to death.
Right? He issues a judgment. Yeah.
Yeah.
David says good.
He's you, right?
That's my how the turn tables have.
Oh, wait.
Yeah.
So, um, but David ends up repenting, right?
David repents.
And so that judgment ends up becoming, for him, this kind of disciplinary, corrective judgment.
Right?
because of how he receives it and what he does in terms of repentance.
So with those kind of ideas of judgment, right, these sort of two senses of two kinds of judgment,
we can kind of go, and I know this is uncharacteristic for us
in the first half to actually talk about the topic, but brace yourselves here, we're in it.
Oh no!
We can now move to talk about what's called...
So end of days as a phrase doesn't occur,
what is usually used in the Hebrew Bible to refer
to that day is the day of Yahweh.
And as we've said before, sometimes it's spelled out
day of Yahweh, translated usually day of the Lord
in English Bibles with Lord and all caps.
Sometimes just referred to as the day as we've said before.
Like in the last episode.
but you're just the day of Yahweh.
that is coming and represents
judgment.
So one of the more
full, complete sort of
descriptions and depictions
of the day of Yahweh comes
in Isaiah as you might expect.
Most of these are going to be
from the prophets announcing
the day of Yahweh.
Yeah, this is this is
killer stuff.
It's a little long.
Don't put a lot of trouble in that door.
Don't put a lot of trouble in that door, Bill.
was that all-killer no-filler?
That's right. Yeah, a little long to put in a billboard, this particular passage, but yeah.
Okay, so Isaiah chapter 13, starting with verse 4,
the weapons of his indignation to destroy the whole land, wail for the day of the Lord
as near as destruction from the Almighty it will come. Therefore all hands will be feeble,
and every human heart will melt. They will be dismayed, pangs, and agony will seize them.
They will be in anguish like a woman in labor. They will look aghast at one another, their
faces will be aflame, behold the day of the Lord comes, cruel with wrath and fierce anger
to make the land a desolation.
destroy its sinners from it. For the stars of the heavens, their consolations will not give
their light, the sun will be dark at its rising, and the moon will not shed its light.
I will punish the world for its evil and the wicked for their iniquity. I will put an
end to the pomp of the arrogant, and lay low the pompous pride of the ruthless. I will
make people more rare than fine gold and mankind than the gold of Ophir. Therefore I will
make the heavens tremble and the earth will be shaken out of its
place, at the wrath of the Lord of hosts in the day of his fierce anger, and like a hunted
gazelle or like sheep with none to gather them, each will turn to his own people and each
will flee to his own land. Whoever is found will be thrust through and whoever is caught
will fall by the sword. Their infants will be dashed in pieces before their eyes, their
houses will be plundered and their wives ravished.
It's pretty rough.
Yeah.
Not something to look forward to.
And you notice that sort of depopulation language that we mentioned too, right?
Maybe humanity rare.
But notice the raretus is they contrasted with gold.
So there's a bit of a word play out the word that's translated rare there.
Okay.
And that it can mean both like there's not a lot of humans left.
And it can mean that humanity kind of gets verified.
humanity kind of gets refined.
Right. But so, yeah, this is a description of the day of Lord. This is apocalyptic in the
contemporary usage, right? Kind of stuff, right? This is in timesy stuff. Here's the thing,
though, we didn't read the first three verses of the chapter. Isaiah is saying this to babble
on.
Hmm, which, you know, by our day is long, long, long, long, long, long gone.
Yeah. Yeah.
And so what he's describing as the day of the Lord, as the day of Yahweh,
as the last day, is what he's detailed describing is the invasion of the
of the needs and the Persians.
To destroy the Neobatelonian Empire.
Yeah, so this kind of language which seems very end of the world kind of stuff is
In in terms of the the human now of Isaiah is an actual sort of historical events that we can point to that happened long in the past for us
Right, so when he says the day is near
He's not saying the end of the world is about to happen
right he's not making it
Jack Vanitype style in Times prediction. Right. He's saying that that day, the day of the
Lord is near, is drawing near to Babylon. Hmm. So we've talked before when we talk about
ritual participation. We've talked about it primarily, not entirely, but primarily in
in terms of participation.
participation in past events.
Right, so we've pointed out, right, the Passover, right, is, you know, this is the night on which God delivered us from Egypt, even when it's celebrated in 2023.
Right.
And it's a participation in that day.
And we've talked about how that extends to the Eucharist,
to Holy Week, to...
things in the life of the church. But so this is also true,
these of you the future. But one of the differences here in the way
that scripture talks about judgment and talks about the day of the Lord
is that this isn't sort of a deliberate participation.
Right? This isn't like the needs of the Persians went and did a religious
ritual.
anticipated the day of judgment and rendered judgment against Babylon and take it over.
No.
Right.
This is the day itself, right?
Judgment itself, the judgment of God, the wrath of God, the day of judgment itself being
portrayed as having like agency, that it's sort of sneaking up on Babylon.
Yeah.
drawing close to them.
Right. It's about to pounce. Judgment is coming. Right. And that call,
right, what that call is aimed at doing is bringing about repentance.
Repentance will not stop that judgment from happening necessarily.
But it will mean that judgment will be different. Right. Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
You know, a book of Jonah as the counter example.
Right.
It doesn't counter it.
But as an example of how it could go, you know, and known as Jonah's prophecy against
Nineveh is just simply, Nineveh is going to be overthrown.
Bad things are happening.
They're going to happen.
And the people repent.
And then God does not do those bad things.
Well, at least at that time.
At that time, right?
I mean, yeah.
Did it get destroyed?
Yes.
I know you can desert.
Yeah.
Who's the one who Isaiah is warning?
That's right.
So yeah, so you're not necessarily
going to avoid the whole, right?
Judgment is not in and of itself an evil,
because it can be corrective.
Yeah, as we said.
It only seems evil if you're out of order.
If you're on the wrong end of it.
Right.
So, yeah.
And so this language, right?
And that's, you know, that's what St. John the Four
Runner is saying when he's saying the axis
of the root of the tree, right?
Like it's, this is it, right?
Judgment is coming for you, Judeans, right?
And it did, right?
Starting, especially at 70 AD, not beginning ending
everything in 80, 70, but beginning there.
That judgement from
God came. And they were warned by a prophet in advance, why so they could repent? That was
his baptism. But so judgment sort of comes back. It's have us moving back through time
to participate, right? This is judgment comes back through time and lays hold.
Right? Of uh...
of nations. Yeah, and I mean, and the purpose is I
especially if you get a profit announcing it beforehand is to to encourage repentance
But also if they if they don't repent it's to limit their evil because they become too harmful
For everyone else there, you know to use the biblical language the cup of their iniquity has has is full right
Yeah, that scale we've talked I know I've talked about it before other show the scale between the outcry of the
That's it.
of violence and and God's patience and mercy toward the perpetrators of sin
eventually shifts the other way and judgment comes. Yeah and so there's a
bunch of other examples we'll read if just a few here from the prophets of the
same thing. Yeah you get the sense of the day of the Lord arriving lots of bad
things happening. So Jeremiah 4610 that day is the
day of the Lord God of hosts to de-avengeance, to avenge himself on his foes. The sword shall
devour and be sated and drink its fill of their blood. For the Lord God of hosts holds
a sacrifice in the North country by the river Euphrates."
So that's very clearly talking about Babylon.
Right, there's a geographical locator.
Yeah, Babylon doesn't come out well if you read the whole Bible.
Yeah. Yeah. Or any random part that mentioned it actually.
Just about yeah, I don't think this
anything really super good said about Babel. So, okay, Zikyll, chapter 30, verses 3 and 4,
for the day is near, the day of the Lord is near. It will be a day of clouds, a time of doom for
the nations. A sword shall come upon Egypt, and anguish shall be in Kush, when the slain fallen
Egypt and her wealth is carried away and her foundations are torn down.
So again, the day of the Lord is near Egypt.
Yeah.
It's near for Egypt, right? That doesn't mean he's saying the end of days is next Tuesday,
right? Right. But it's coming for Egypt soon is what he's saying. Yeah. So,
Obadiah chapter 1 verse 15, for the day of the Lord is near upon all the nations. As you have
done, it shall be done to you, your deeds shall return on your own head. So that's everybody.
Yep, all the missions.
All of you.
all y'all. Joel chapter 2 verse 31, the sun shall be turned to darkness and the moon to blood
before the great and awesome day of the Lord comes. Right and that's I think we talked about this last
time last episode. This prophecy from Joel that gets quoted on Pentecost, right, but you notice the
language.
there that's attached to the death of Christ, right? And say Peter really preaches this,
is interpreting this as Christ's death, is followed by the pouring out of the Spirit,
right, on all flesh, but that's also a sign of judgment that's coming upon Judea
by way of the Romans as instrument. And so, again, there's this kind of agency where judgment
just as comes back.
sort of through time and finds some nation, right?
And its judgment happens that day.
That day becomes the day of Yahweh,
the day of the Lord for that nation, right, at that time.
And we can say that about going forward too,
if we have a Christian understanding of history, right?
So, Saint Augustine understood in City of God
That's what was happening.
happening to Rome, to Old Rome, in his day, right, that judgment was coming.
Yeah.
When you read what, especially monastic fathers living at the time of the fall of Constantinople
said, right, they mourned the fall of Constantinople just like, you know, the book of lamentations,
mourns the fall of Jerusalem to the Babylonians.
But there was also an awareness among them that there were reasons why this happened.
This was judgment from God.
Yeah.
Right.
That had come upon the city.
Yeah.
But so, as we were talking about before, those are all examples with nations, right?
Those are macrocosm examples.
But the same dynamic is true in the microcosmic level, the level of a human person, right?
And so the, the, the surfers will talk about judgment and.
terms of the death of an individual human person. And again, judgment is not always negative.
It's not always being cut off, right? So this doesn't mean that a person dies, right?
This is a judgment in the negative sense always, right?
Yeah, I mean, in, in, in some ways, it might be easier if we use the word like discernment,
God's discernment. You're not so much into that.
I'm not a fan. Yeah.
to Wimpy. Yeah, well, there's a whole discernment blogging.
which is just, yeah. I wish it was just blogs these days. But you know, the idea of
of God turning his eye on the situation and sizing it up, this is how it is.
So you know, you can, you can pass a test. You don't always fail. There is also contained an idea
of consequences. Yeah, right, right. Right. Right. Not that God is actively punishing.
but that he's now no longer mercifully restraining
the consequences.
Yeah, right, right, right.
So yeah, and so this is why,
like Hebrews 927 says that it's appointed for man
wants to die and then the judgment.
And the judgment.
I know the old King James Version.
Yeah.
And I think it's in vents the judgment, actually.
But this relates to, of course,
and we've talked about this before,
but our understanding of prayers for the dead,
and how that relates to judgment, right?
So one of the things, people who haven't come,
people who've come out of a tradition
that rejects the idea of praying for the departed,
I'll put it that way.
Because let me just say there are plenty of Protestants
to even though on paper.
they don't believe in praying for departed people who do pray for their departed loved ones.
I mean, I literally was at a dinner last night where a Protestant pastor told the assembled
who were there about how he led one of his prisoners in prayer for her departed mother.
So yeah, yeah.
So there are certain folks who come from a tradition that rejects it and so they have
an issue. One of the...
So we say objections that is raised is, well, if the person's dead, right, they're dead.
You want to dive in the judgment, right?
So they've already experienced the day of the Lord.
They've already experienced a day of judgment, right?
And the problem with that, of course, as we talked about a bunch of times on the show,
how we experience time is not absolute, right?
So yes.
Insofar as we're able to understand what it would be like to be a
disembodied person which is not much, but yeah
We understand that they are in some way
From their perspective participating in that judgment participating in the day of the Lord, right?
That they're not sitting around in a waiting room, right because they don't have a
Body to sit right
or to take up a room.
From what we do know, what we're intimately familiar with,
is our own experience of time, right, at our own world, right?
And from my perspective and my experience of time, right,
the day of the Lord is in the future, right.
For me, it is in the future.
And so when I pray, I'm praying from my perspective,
individual human subject, right? I'm not making a universal cosmic prayer. I'm not there
may be someone who could do that, but it's not me. I'm trying to put some words together
right? I'd like to talk to God. And so from my perspective, the judgment is not yet here.
It's in my future. And on a future day, I will be standing beside this person who I'm praying
for. But that's in the future for me.
And so I pray about it.
And that has nothing to do with the idea that that person has some agency to repent, as
we've talked about before.
It has to do with me offering my prayers to God.
And God who does not exist in time or experience a succession of moments can choose to use
my prayers as part of how he saves that person.
he wants to, just like he could choose to use my prayers. If I pray for someone to be healed,
he could choose to use my prayers. That's one of the things by which he heals that person.
If God so chooses doesn't need him, but he can graciously choose to work through them if he
if he wants to. All right, well, that's the first half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits
on Doomsday. We're going to take a short break and we'll be right back in a moment.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and
or Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
This is Father Stephen Freeman. I'm happy to announce ancient face publication of my latest book,
face to face knowing God.
beyond our shame.
Some modern therapists have described shame as the master emotion, one that colors and
shapes our world in ways that we hardly imagine.
The Christian tradition is no stranger to this and has a rich understanding of the ways
this part of our inner life shapes our experience of the world.
This book offers something of a roadmap to that inner life.
What is shame?
Is it always bad?
Does it have any useful purpose for us?
Join me in an exploration of knowing God beyond our shame.
Finding the true God whom the scriptures tell us
did not turn his face from the spitting and the shame.
Face to face is now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
That's store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Smashing.
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now
at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back. It's the second half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits. We're talking about
the judgment day, doomsday, the end.
of the world. So yeah, we talked about the day, the day of the Lord in the last half. And
this one, we're going to continue on our conversation and especially look at some stuff from
the New Testament, talking about that moment and what it means to be judged and all that kind
of stuff. So it's my understanding the New Testament teaches that you're judged according to
to a little list of doctrines you agree with, is that right?
Absolutely correct.
Good night everybody.
Yeah.
There's a quiz.
There's a theology quiz.
It's true false.
So even if you don't know what you're doing, you have 50-50 shot.
There you go.
Yeah.
So no cheating.
So it actuality.
This may be shocking to some people.
In fact, this whole half may be shocking to a whole
ton of people.
But every place in Scripture that talks about the day of judgment, the day of yawai, that
talks about the basis for that judgment.
What it is on what is it that people are judged?
criteria.
when they're separated out, right? So that macrocosmic judgment we were talking about, right?
Every single one, including every single one of the New Testament,
says that we're judged according to our works. Things you do. Yes. And don't do. You do.
or left undone. Yes. That is the basis. That sounds like we're
for righteousness until
Uncle Steve. Yes, well, get ready for it. So this is the only positive teaching on this
founded the New Testament. We're talking mainly in this half, this second half about the
New Testament, right? Because I know we got some folks out there who be like, well, yeah,
Or is that works for action in the magnet or no Old Testament, right?
Then pair.
But not the New Testament.
That's where it all changed, right?
Unfortunately, no.
In the New Testament, everywhere it is positively taught
that we are judged according to our works,
according to what we have done in this life or left undone.
That is the teaching of the whole New Testament without exception.
right without exception.
Do you hear that buzzing we may have to edit this?
Was there seriously do you hear it or no?
No, no.
Oh, I have allowed buzzing.
There we go.
It went away from me.
Okay.
Snip.
So this is
This is what's taught ever. There's no exception. There's no, this is what happens if you're not in Christ.
Yeah, right. There's no. This is how it works for non-Christians. There's no get out of the house.
Free card. Yeah. This is how it works for every human. Right. And we're not just going to start that. Let's give some examples.
The first one is the one time that Christ addresses this.
Hmm.
Where Christ explicitly says, when the judgment, so he references that judgment, we've already
quoted, for example, the parable of the weeds, right?
That's talking about the judgment, right?
Wheat goes in the barn, weeds go in the fire, right?
But it doesn't say what the basis is for deciding who's wheat and who's weeds, right?
So the one place where he lays out, okay, here's the difference between the two is
in what's you often referred to as the parable of the sheep in the goats, which is we read
on the Sunday of the last judgment in the Orthodox Church.
Matthew 20, sorry, for let.
And so here he describes not just, hey, goats and sheep are going to get separated, sheep
goat heaven, goats go to hell, right?
But what makes someone a sheep and what makes someone a goat?
And this is in, we're not going to read the whole thing because this is fairly familiar.
It's Matthew 25 versus 31 through 46.
Right.
So you can...
This is a bit where Jesus says, you know, to those on this right hand, when I was hunger,
you fed me when I was thirst, you gave me drink, when I was sick in prison, you visited me.
You know, when you always naked, you clothed me that right.
And so those on this left, he says, I was those things and you did not help me.
Right.
And both groups say when did we see you?
And he said, when you did it for the least of these,
so you did it to me.
Yeah, right.
So this is very clearly, it's not even one group did good things
and the other group did evil things.
Yeah, no, it's one group did good things
and the other group did no things.
Yeah, just didn't do those things.
Yes.
Yeah, I mean, it's interesting.
Like some people have the sense,
like I'll be okay.
the judgment because I did not do this list of bad things. But when, as you said, when Jesus
specifically addresses us, he didn't say, you know, well, you go, it's your out of here because you
murdered, you raped, you pillaged, you stole. It's, you didn't do the good that was presented to you.
That's what he says. As St. James says, and it's a pistol, he who knows the good he ought to do and
doesn't do it since. That's pretty unambiguous. Yeah so.
Right? But so this is it. There's no way to read this parable.
Both groups refer to him as Lord, by the way, in the parable.
Hmm.
The goats say, Lord, when did we see you like this?
Right? So it's not that one group acknowledges Jesus as Lord and the other one doesn't.
Yeah.
Right? There's no way to read this parable and get anything else out of it.
other than this is a ch...
by works, right? There just isn't. There's not even special pleading possible.
Right? The other big important piece here, of course, is how this works.
Right? Because of course, if Christ is going to tell us, hey, when that final judgment comes,
When the day comes when you stand before my judgment seat, here's the
by which you're going to be judged. Why is he telling us that so that we know how to order our lives?
Right in preparation for that
I mean, that's the obvious context. He's not just saying this for general interest
Right, oh by the way for those of you who are wondering how the last judgment works. Here's how it works, right? No, this is pointed right
He's telling it is a parable
two people so that they can live accordingly so that they can do accordingly.
right? And so this means he's not just describing the basis of that judgment, but he's also describing the basis of
the Christian life, of Christian ethics, of the way Christians are to live in the world. And
in separate, I mean the basis of that for him here is the idea of
the veneration of the image of God in other human persons.
Hmm.
Right? It's again, inescapable here, right? The whole idea is that if I give a cup of water
to someone who is thirsty, right, I am giving that cup of water to Christ. That act that
I perform ultimately, that respect, that honor that I give to that person, that good thing
that I do for that person is a good thing I'm doing for Christ. It's honor and respect
I'm giving you.
to Christ by giving it to that human person, even the least human person.
And vice versa, the disrespect, the dishonor, right?
Also this dishonor, disrespect going to Christ.
So this is the basis of our Christian ethic toward each other according to Christ, right?
This is the basis of how he live.
So if you're someone who is of an iconic plastic bent.
Right? Who rejects this principle? Who rejects the idea that the honor bestowed on the image passes to the prototype?
You've got a real problem not just with this parable but with Christian ethics.
Hmm. Because if the honor I give to another human person doesn't pass from them as the image of God to God Himself,
Then that means if I do something good for another human, I'm doing it for them.
as opposed to doing it for Christ.
Yeah, instead of Christ, you know, they get in the way.
Right. Right. Right.
If you deny that it passes, right?
So if you're going to say me honoring an icon, showing honor to an icon, or
reverence to an icon of Christ, is somehow idolatry, or if you don't want to drop the idolatry word
in some way.
distancing me from Christ, right? The same would be true when I do good for a person.
The same would be true when a servant obeys their master, contra what St. Paul says.
You should obey them as the Lord.
Yeah, why not just obey the Lord directly? That would be instead, right? And so if you're
You're going to go down that road if you're going to be a consistent
iconoclast, you have to go down like the Christian anarchist road, no king but Christ,
right, where you give no honor to the government, the civil authorities,
Contra St. Paul, because that would be instead of Christ.
Right. You're going to have to, how can you divide your time?
You're going to have to become some kind of proto-monastic hermit, right? Because time you spend with
your wife and kids is time you're not spending with Christ.
If you take that iconoclastic argument seriously, right?
Now of course, people don't.
People only apply that argument to orthodox icons and apologetics against orthodox people.
But as Christians, they have to acknowledge that principle everywhere else, ethically,
or Christian ethics holds apart.
Yeah.
Right?
it's based in this
And by the way, I'm going to say it's not just a series of commands of things you're
supposed to be doing.
Right.
Jesus gives a reason for it.
Yeah.
Right.
Like I don't love my brother just because God told me to.
I love my brother because in loving my brother, I am actually loving God.
Right.
That's what he says.
But by the way, by the
way, just to further complicate this, the doctrine of the Holy Trinity is based on this
principle, too. Most people don't actually understand the
doctrine of the Holy Trinity, well enough to understand why iconoclasm wrecks it. But
if you read the place where that principle I've been referring to, the honor of interracial
and worship.
Give it.
into an object passes to the prototype, right?
Given to an image passes to the prototype, right?
The place where that principle first gets laid out
in those terms is not any argument about iconography.
It's St. Basil the Great talking about the Holy Trinity.
In terms of why we as Christians aren't tri-fists,
why we don't worship three gods.
Because the worship we give to Christ.
passes to God the Father. Yeah. And I mean, and that's why we're monotheists,
and monolatrous. Yeah. I was gonna say I mean, there's other places where it's not
just that the worship of Christ is the worship of the Father, but also like Christ
Himself says things like, if you've seen me, you've seen the Father, you know,
they hated both me and my Father. Like there's always this sense that the way you treat
Jesus. He does not speak on his own authority. He speaks the words of his Father.
Yeah, I must be about my father's business.
you know how are we to treat Jesus as how you're treating the Father? Right. Right. And so it's not just
all of Christian ethics that falls apart if you're an icon of class. It's the doctrine of the Holy
Trinity and Christology. Yeah. So it's not just a question of I get that some folks, especially in
US kind of phobic culture of touching things and kissing things right.
Other cultures men walk up and kiss each other on either cheek all the time to say hi, right?
We don't do that in the US. I know you think kissing pictures or kissing anything is kind of
icky and weird, but the correct response to that to being kind of icked out by that is not to
deny the fundamental principle of Christian theology. Let me just suggest that. Let me just throw
that out there, Gavin Orland. Anyway, sorry, I didn't mean anyone in particular.
Um, yeah.
So if anyone is actually consistent with that, they won't end up being a Christian.
Fortunately, people are completely inconsistent about that.
They just want to apply it to iconography.
But this is why Orthodox Christians have been saying ever since iconoclasm first reared
its ugly head.
Iconoclasm was a fairly late development in church history.
and then iconic class in first read,
since it first read, just ugly head.
This is why Orthodox Christians have defended the principles of iconography so strictly is because we're defending this principle.
Because if you let go of this principle, your Christology falls apart.
Your view of Christian life falls apart.
The doctor of the Holy Trinity falls apart.
And so this isn't just some ancillary thing.
Yeah, that just has to do with your church decor.
Right.
Right
whether you should just look at the iconography or kiss it, right? This is of critical importance
to Christianity. So, yeah, people who haven't understood how that works yet shouldn't
start pulling out jangle blocks when they don't know how the towers bill. So anyway, all that
said. That was not.
off top right that's no right these are some of the critically important to
understand right with right to say the works that we're gonna be judged on yes
deeds so it's also important right that if someone were wanting to argue with us
and say, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, this judgment by work stuff, huh?
bad. The works ready is bad, right? There go to is probably going to be St Paul. Yeah,
and probably Romans, especially. Right. That's who they're going to go to. That's where
the perspective from which they're going to try to come come back at us. But what does
St Paul say? Starting in Romans, when St Paul talks about the basis on which we are going
to be judged.
Here we go.
So yeah, Romans chapter two, starting with verse five and going through 11.
But because of your hard and impenitant or unrepentant heart, you are storing up wrath for yourself
on the day of wrath when God's righteous judgment will be revealed.
He will render to each one according to his works, to those who by patience and well-doing
seek for glory and honor and immortality, he will give you eternal life.
But for those who are self-seeking
and do not obey the truth, but obey unrighteousness,
there will be wrath and fury.
There will be tribulation and distress
for every human being who does evil,
the Jew first and also the Greek.
But glory and honor and peace for everyone who does good,
For God shows no partiality.
So,
there's not really a way to get around this one either.
Right? So someone might say, well, St. Paul isn't talking about like the final judgment,
like who goes to heaven and who goes to hell, right? Not that that's our eschatology as
Christians anyway, right? This isn't talking about eternal life and eternal condemnation.
This is talking about like we're a ward, there's a judgment of works, but that's like,
you know, you get jewels in your crown or something. Yeah. I mean, I've heard literally
that, you know, essentially like, well, you know, whether you get in and out is one question
but kind of how big your mansion is or how nice.
your heaven heavenly rolls rice is is what this is about. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
There's just some people get it up in the heaven slum and some people. Yeah.
Problem with that, right? He says he'll render to each one according to his works to those who
buy patients in well-doing seek for glory and honor and immortality. He will give eternal life.
Yeah. It's about eternal life.
And in more time they write just this, they'll be wrath and fury.
It's patience in doing good is literally what he says.
Those who seek for glory and honor and immortality
by patience in doing good.
Yep, receive eternal life at the day of judgment.
According to St. Paul.
Yep, and tribulation to distress
for every human being who does evil.
Right, and this isn't, he's not talking about,
this isn't a place where St. Paul is like doing this
rhetorical thing.
Right.
He's not saying, oh, well, this is the way it worked in the old covenant.
But now we're going to something new because notice he says for the Jew first and also for the Greek.
Yeah, the place to judge.
Greeks weren't included in the old covenant.
Yeah.
Yep.
And not just Greeks, Greeks, the Greek is the nations.
It's sort of everybody else in the Judeans in the same place.
Right.
You saw, we have Gentiles.
Yeah.
Right.
Jews are Gentiles.
So this is talking about
Christ's judgments.
right? And there's not a place, and this isn't St. Paul sort of problematizing to then give you a
way out. Right? Because you notice he doesn't say here, therefore everyone stands condemned.
There's to be wrath and fury for everyone. He most definitely doesn't say that.
Yeah, there's no sense of well, if you but now you're off the hook. Yeah, or even if you do
you
you get glory in honor and immortality, but no one does good.
So yeah, but you can't.
Right? He doesn't. He doesn't. Right? And it's important. Right? Verse 5.
We didn't just include verse 5 because he talks about the day of wrath when God's righteous judgment
is revealed just to locate this on the day of judgment. But why is it that the people he's speaking to,
or how is it?
that they're storing up wrath for themselves on the day of judgment.
Because they have a heart that is hard and unrepentant.
The word that's translated unrepentant there is Amitanoeton, which is made here metania in there
without repentance. It's got an alpha on the front, right? Alpha-Pay repentance, your lack of repentance.
Yeah, right.
And that's about what you do.
It's not about what you think or what you feel.
It's about what you do.
So the answer to this, for what St. Paul says here, the answer to this is not for these
people he's talking to, to believe something, think something, change their mind in terms
of their thoughts about something, it's to repent of the evil they've done.
and to begin to patiently seek to do good.
That's what he presents the solution as.
Which, so what St. Paul says here,
not really any different than what St. John the Four
on her saying.
Or what Christ was saying,
the parallel to sheep of the goats.
Right?
This is a judgment by works.
Therefore, repent and seek to do good.
It's amazing.
Thank you.
I do, and I don't, I'm not using amazing rhetorically.
It does amaze me sometimes.
When I sit back and think that one of the most controversial things
you could say in American Christian circles is that Christians
ought to try not to commit sins and to go and do good things
that are pleasing to God.
Like you
you would think like yeah.
Right?
But as someone who has said that publicly
in mixed American Christian company,
you get accused of teaching works righteousness.
How dare you?
Yeah.
People did.
I mean, like righteousness.
So we could dead cat in the Bible.
I don't know why you'd be swinging a dead cat in the Bible,
but if you can't swing a dead cat in the Bible,
without hitting that.
Yeah.
I mean, righteousness.
is like whenever a righteous person is described, he or she is described by the way that he lives.
That's what it means to be righteous. You know, I mean, some people might argue that say,
oh, we've got the righteousness of God and not our own. It's just this filthy rags, blah, blah,
but that's not about, you know, your good deeds are worth nothing. It's, that's a person repenting.
Right, it's, you know, did you?
You know, it's not you came up with your own impressive things
that you think are gonna get you saved,
like your own feats of heroism, right?
That's what's being spoken against there.
That's the garbage.
You know, if you do the things that God has given you to do,
that's not filthy rags.
Yes.
That's what God's works.
But yes, give too many spoilers.
Loving your brother and killing your brother
are not equally sinful.
Right on those-
is pleasing to God and the other one is not exactly exactly right like yeah and yes I know
even when I love my brother my motives are never pure and da da da da da da da da da da da da
still more pleasing to God than me murdering him yeah yeah yeah um yep so we've gotten to this
weird place. And I don't think we're in that weird place in the
real world, right? Our Protestant friends who would get the most mad at me for the way
I'm talking right now on the theoretical level. If you look at how they actually live
their life, they try not to commit sins and they try to do good for people. Yeah. Now,
they functionally do it. But if you say it, it sounds wrong to them, right? On this ideological
You think you're adding something to your savvy?
right. Yeah. And of course not. And they don't think that when they're out doing good things for people to help people.
Right. Yeah. But again, so we need to get past this, right? If the scriptures feel totally fine about talking this way, we can talk this way too.
Yeah. And if the scriptures talk this way consistently all through the New Testament as we're showing here, then maybe any idea we've come up with
with theologically that conflicts with that we should just...
dumpster it. Yeah. And go with the way the Bible talks about it. Yeah.
Have it some more examples. Yes, another example from St. Paul in 2 Corinthians. Yeah. Okay. So 2 Corinthians chapter 5
verses 6 through 10. So we are always of good courage. We know that while we are at home in the body
we are away from the Lord for we walk by faith, not by sight. Yes, we are of good courage
and we would rather be away from the body and at home with
the Lord. So whether we, whether we are at home or away, we make it our aim to please him.
For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ so that each one may receive what is
due for what he has done in the body, whether good or evil. Yes. So before the judgment seat of
Christ, we're judged for what we have done. Yeah, and it's notable here that he says we almost
appear before the judgment seat of Christ. He doesn't say but it
If you believe that Jesus is your savior
and accept him as Lord of your life,
then you don't have to appear
before the judgment seat of Christ.
Get out of judgment free card.
Yeah, and he says we're all gonna appear
and we're all gonna receive what we've done in the body.
That's pretty worksy.
You know, it's about your body,
like what you do with your body.
And the reason we read those first few verses is,
right, that four at the beginning of verse 10,
four we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ.
That's because.
Yeah, that's why we want.
by faith, not by sight. Right. The effect of that, right, our knowledge that we're going to have to
appear before the judgment seat of Christ to receive what is due, whether good or evil for what we've
done in this life is what causes us in this life to try to live our lives faithfully in a way that is
pleasing to Christ. Because it's actually critical. What we do in this life is actually critical.
That's the way that's pleasing to Christ.
just bone right not just because you'll be kind of embarrassed but get eternal life anyway.
Zalusapal says yeah right. All right next one and other New Testament authors
yeah should be no surprise don't disagree with him. Yeah same Peter for instance
uh first Peter chapter one verse 17 just one verse and if you call on him as Father who judges
M.
partially according to each one's deeds, conduct yourselves with fear throughout the time of your exile.
Right? So God is going to judge you according to your deeds, according to your works.
Therefore, conduct yourself with fear of God, with awe and reverence toward that judgment throughout the time of your life in this world.
All right, we'll back to St. Paul.
Colossians chapter 3 verses 23 through 25.
Whatever you do, work heartily as for the Lord and not for men.
Knowing that from the Lord you will receive the inheritance as your reward.
You are serving the Lord Christ.
For the wrong doer will be paid back for the wrong he has done.
And there is no partiality.
So once again, this is...
Saint Paul like problematizing. Like this is what we face, but now just believe in Jesus. Right,
Ed, you avoid all this. He never says that. Right. He never says that. Now there is one place where
Christ talks about judgment that some people might see as being slightly different.
Yeah, yeah, so this is Matthew chapter 12
Where the Lord says either make the tree good and its fruit good or make the tree bad and its fruit bad
For the tree is known by its fruit
You brutive vipers how can you speak good when you are evil?
For the out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks
The good person out of his good treasure brings forth good and the evil person out of his evil treasure brings forth evil
I tell you on the
day of judgment. People will give account for every careless word they speak. For by
your words, you will be justified and by your words, you will be condemned. So, you can
see how some people might take that, especially those last bits as saying, well, it's about
the things that you say you believe, your words, you know, just going to justify your
condemn you. But he wasn't just talking about believing.
Right, right. He's talking about a good person and a bad person.
Right? And that there are the acts of speaking, the things that come out of their mouth. Right?
Those are actions. Right? As Christ says, the person who says there's brother you fool has already murdered him in his heart. That's what he's talking about here. Right?
So this is not a different standard. This is Christ clarifying that standard. Right?
That saying lured things
and engaging in sexual immorality
are not two different things
where one's okay and the other one isn't.
Yeah.
Saying mean things to people
but not actually putting your hands on them
is not like, okay.
Right?
And this is not, you know, sometimes this stuff gets it,
oh Christ is making the law more intense, right?
It's like that was already in the Torah.
It's just interpreting it for people
have been interpreting it.
in correctly to justify their own behavior.
He's interpreting them correctly.
Because just use the 10 commandments, right?
What is covetousness, if not the thoughts
that precede stealing?
Yeah.
What is coveting a man's wife, if not the thoughts
that precede adultery?
Yeah.
Right.
This isn't changing the Torah, right?
It's just you had a bunch of people he was talking to
who were saying, well, you know,
thought about him.
I didn't do it. So, you know, he's like, no, no, no, no, no, thinking about it is doing something.
And that's already there, but the commandments, right? So that's not really an outlier.
It still works, right? But that includes the words that come out of your mouth,
not just the things you do with your hands and your rest of your body.
Yeah.
And so then we started with Matthew.
We said the hold.
New Testament. So more or less, ending up near the end of the book of Revelation.
Yeah, well, we are talking about judgment. So we do need a little apocalypse, right?
So Revelation chapter 20, verse 12, and I saw the dead, great and small standing before
the throne and books were opened. Then another book was opened, which is the book of life.
and the dead were judged.
by what was written in the books,
according to what they had done.
That's what's in the book of life.
Yeah.
And that is Revelation, chapter 20, verse 12,
because the world is coming to an end in 2012.
I knew it.
Uh, so,
because chapters and verses were written there
by the apostles, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
They were authorized.
It's the authorized version.
So, right. So, these books are opened. Well, books are those. We've talked about this
a little bit on previous episodes of the show. These heavenly books, earlier than that,
in the Asian areas, they're heavenly tablets, right? Sometimes, so in some second-tabled
Jewish sources, like the book of Jubilee's, you've got an angelic being who sort of records
everything that's happening on earth.
everything everybody does. Sometimes the books are just there, right? We don't get like an explicit description of who's doing the writing or you know
that kind of thing. But the books are there with everything everyone has done, right? And we've also talked before about the book of life, the idea of a name being in the book of life being related to divine memory, right? This is
to be remembered by God means you can because God is eternal means eternal.
right? This is eternal life to know you the only true God, right? And this is why of course, as we've
said before, this is why we sing memory eternal in the Orthodox Church at Memorial Services. May the
person's memory be eternal, right? If they're remembered by God, their name is in the book of life,
right? But of course people can be blotted out of the book of life. We read about names being
being plotted out of the book of life repeatedly in the Scriptures.
And that means, you know, the names are raised, the name is gone.
This is a person who's forgotten and abandoned by God.
This is an image of condemnation.
So yes, once again, here's the standard.
It's works.
It's what people have done.
So are we on Lord of Spirits teaching works righteousness?
Yes.
in one sense.
Yeah, because, because again, you know,
to live to be a righteous person is someone who lives
the right way and righteousness equals justice.
That's right.
That's the same word in Greek.
Yeah. Yeah.
So, right, the idea is if a person is righteous,
they are right.
They are rightly ordered, not just internally,
but rightly ordered in terms of their
with God and other people, right?
And that is not a different thing
from how they live their life.
It doesn't mean they're right with God
and other people on the inside,
but you know, are degenerates
in the way they live their life, right?
That dog don't hunt, right?
You can't be regenerate and a degenerate
at the same time, sorry Martin Luther.
Um, the uh...
So yeah, when it says in Genesis 6 that Noah was righteous from his generation, right?
That doesn't mean he lived his life exactly like everybody else, but he had had a foreign
righteousness freely imputed to him.
That's not what that means.
Yeah, it means he's going to be.
And you're doing unbelievable amount of Isis Jesus to say that's what it means, right?
Beats.
The way he lived was fundamentally different than the way the other people in the world
were living whose thoughts were always evil all the time were told in Genesis.
Yeah.
Right.
His weren't.
Okay.
Um, that's not.
But also, are we teaching on Lord of Spirits works for righteousness also?
No.
Because what people usually make well
I was going to say what people usually mean,
but I don't think it's clear,
and I think that's part of the problem.
Yeah, I mean, I remember, I don't think...
When I was being brought up in, you know,
low church evangelical circles,
I mean, this was talked about all the time,
and it was constantly said,
there's nothing you can do to earn your way to heaven.
It's a free gift from God.
Your righteousness is filthy rags before the Lord, you know,
And so there's
this idea, you know, well, those Catholics, they probably hadn't heard of the Orthodox.
So those Catholics think they can earn their way to heaven with their good deeds.
Like, this is the whole matrix in which this was talked exactly like that, exactly like
that.
I must have heard a thousand sermons that that was basically the message, you know.
And so what people talk about works righteous and assess what they generally mean is they
think you think you can do enough good deeds and earn your way to heaven.
Right.
And...
But that's not the problem is I think that's not sufficiently disambiguated in most people's minds from just,
hey, as a Christian, you ought to try to, to, to good in the world.
Right.
And I think at least some of the reformers would have wanted to disambiguate that.
The reason I always say some of the reformers is, this is another one of the places.
Uh...
And this is a place where we've just got to go there,
Protestant friends.
This is one of the places where Protestantism
in the 16th century and 17th century
was understandably reactionary against Roman Catholicism,
right, against Rome.
But that reactionary stance has remained
for another coming up on.
400 years that it didn't need to.
Yeah, I mean, they're reacting against this Roman Catholic idea.
The evil Roman Catholic system.
Yeah, they're reacting against this idea that there's, and I will, I think I'm in as mispronounceable,
but I don't mean to.
Serp super erogatory works or merit.
Don't at me, people.
Um, not going to make you, but I'm going to make you
explain the difference between con-dine and congruent.
Oh, don't do that.
No, I mean, there's this idea that the saints,
they did everything that was required for them
to get to heaven.
And but they did extra.
And that extra can be repurposed for ordinary people
to help them.
I mean that's basically...
the idea of the sort of treasure house of merit. I know I know Roman Catholic friends that I'm
probably oversimplifying, but I'm just trying to simple let's just cut to the chase on that.
Okay okay Roman Catholic friends okay. One of the memes out there is that Lord of Spirits is always
is misrepresenting Roman Catholicism, okay?
There's a basic problem right now
within the Church of Rome.
And that is that it is unclear what the teaching of the Church of Rome is on any topic.
But, but, but, because I come on this show, I have literally quoted documents that have
official standing in the Roman Catholic Church and been accused of representing Roman Catholic
policies.
Yeah.
I have, yeah, anyway, I have quoted Cardinals who are heads of Vatican Congresses and have
been told I'm misrepresenting Roman Catholicism.
Well, that's because they're misrepresenting Roman Catholic.
Right.
Exactly.
I don't know.
There's a lot of Roman Catholics who think Pope Francis represents Roman Catholic.
He's the Pope.
Right.
I mean, I know.
So many that feel that way.
So look.
Right.
The best we could do on this show is try to quote members of the Magisterium and official documents.
Okay.
And if you think those are a misrepresentation,
your issue is not...
with me or with Father Andrew, your issue is with the people issuing those documents
and the people who said those quotes.
Okay, because that's all we have to go on.
Yeah.
That's all we have to go on.
But yeah, I mean, so the, and the reformation is reacting against this idea that historically
right, in the, you know, pre-counter reformation, it's pretty darn clear, and I think hard to
RQ-Wap. That Roman Catholicism was T-
and this is what the Reformers are reacting against, right?
That grace received in the lives of people
through the sacraments, right?
Enabled them to in various ways a crew merit.
By different means, right?
So there's condi-american, crew-american.
I'm not going to go at all that now.
I do actually know the difference,
but I'm not going to go at all that now.
to a crew marriage.
which merit when it reached a certain point, right, qualified one for eternal life. That is not,
that is not even that, right, that the Reformation objective to, even that is not
Pelagianism, okay. Pelagianism is the idea that you don't need grace for salvation.
Yeah, they can really truly do it all on your own. So that merit is always produced even in
that medieval Roman Catholic system, that merit was always produced by the work of grace,
although grace was seen as a quantifiable created substance.
That's a whole other debate.
But it was always produced by grace in the person's life.
So it's not polyagionism.
And that saints accrued more merit than was required for eternal life.
that merit goes into the treasury.
That treasury is accessible by the keys of St. Peter.
and can be given out, that merit can be given out in the form of grace, right, by in particular
the Bishop of Rome, right, the Pope of Rome. And that's the system they're reacting against.
Yeah, right. Yeah. And so they saw that, the reformers saw that, right, and did not, this is
This is why I say it's a reactionary position.
They didn't.
throw the whole thing out and start over from the Bible.
They didn't and they don't claim to.
Many many evangelical prizes today talk like they did,
but Luther Calvin would smack you upside the head and he said,
told them they threw everything out and started over.
No one can actually do that.
Even though they're trying really hard.
But what they said was they agreed,
Yes, there's a certain
amount of merit you need for eternal life, but Christ earned it all. And the whole thing
gets imputed into your account all at once when you're justified. Boom. Right. That's
it. Right. And so it's not related to the things you do. It's not even related to
the sacraments. The reformers did say the sacraments are means of grace, but they meant that
another sense it sanctifying race again I'm not
going all that now, right? I'm mentioning it just because again, we'd get added by a bunch of
people, right? We all, I'm sure we will. I'm sure the same. We will anyway. This thing will
put you all a little bit of that. Right, right. But so the reason why we're not teaching any kinds of
any kind of works righteousness, even if you consider the medieval Roman system to be works righteousness,
Right is it that that's what that's how we say because we don't we don't think there's a
There's a threshold.
Yeah, there's not a certain amount that you need.
There's no merit coming into the equation here.
Right?
We're going to talk about that at all.
So there is a sense in which we can say salvation is by works.
Right?
And that is in the sense of theurgy,
which is today's secret word.
Everybody's screamer roll out every time Father Stephen says,
Yes, PRG. Yes, or if someone says
it without having heard this episode, you can give them $100.
I guess that's even more obscure reference.
But, right, the Urgy, literally the works of God.
Yeah.
That probably tells you where we're going.
In this case, the etymology works very well.
Right?
Yeah.
Well, because it's a coinage.
Yeah, it's because they're like, okay, let's make up a word.
Let's make a word.
Yeah.
Right.
So we are saved by works, but it's God's works.
not some independent works of ours.
Yeah, so the point then of saying that we believe in works righteousness
that we teach that is that and that we're going to be judged according to our works because that's
everywhere in the New Testament is that our works the good things that we do actually come from God.
And so when we do those, God is doing them. Yeah, God is doing them. When we do those things,
then we are participating in the works of God.
If I give $100 to my church, it's not just that God gave me that $100.
It's that God is giving $100 to the church, and I'm just participating in it.
And when-
You're giving that $100 to God.
Yeah, and I'm giving it to God, right?
And so when I do that, it also transforms me.
It changes me.
I actually become righteous.
I'm not just imputed as righteous.
I'm not just said to be right.
I actually am righteous when I do righteous things.
You know, you become, you actually become righteous.
Yep.
Not because you've earned that status.
Yeah, I didn't earn it.
Right.
But with your cooperation, not against your will.
With your cooperation, right?
God has made you more righteous.
God has shared His righteousness with you.
Right.
Right. And right, this is justice or this.
word, he is putting you back in order and putting your relationships with him and with other people back in order.
Right? But that's a process pruning, remember? Yep. That takes place over time. Right? And so doing the
works of God, right? Participating in the works of God, God can look at those works when they're done
and call them good because they're his. Does there is? Yep. Right. I can't muster up enough love
me to love all the people I'm supposed to love and to love them the way I should. But God loves
them that way already. And so when I show God's love to them, which is ultimately showing God's love
to God, remember the whole iconography thing, right? I know and over that, I know and all that.
that, then that is transformative for me and for the recipient of God's love.
And that is how God is transfiguring us and the world.
Part of the problem here too, I think, is that, I know I've mentioned this on the show
before, is that we have the relationship between beliefs, thoughts, ideas, the things we believe,
ideas we hold to be true and our life and the way we live.
Yeah, we tend to think like, well...
Once I agree with this, once I understand this, then I'll do it.
Right, we say people's beliefs. If you believe the right things, right? So you have the right theology in your head,
then you'll live your life the correct way, right? Because your beliefs affect the way you live.
Yeah. And that is false. Yeah. Yeah. If that were true, there would be no hypocrites.
Right, right.
right? Yeah. That is just patently not true. Yeah. I mean, the end of Roman chapter seven.
Yeah. And I've seen the good I want to do. I do not do. Yeah. Exactly. I want to do
it. It's the same Paul knew it very, very well. Believe it. Very, very well. Yeah. Uh, yeah. And I've
seen, you know, and I've seen this honestly, I mean, you and I've both seen this past story, right?
Where someone maybe doesn't understand something or doesn't know how they feel about it or whatever,
right, you know, very kind of modern American.
ways of talking. And you encourage them, well look, do this. You know, pray this daily
prayer role. Do this. You know, when you come to church, make the sign of the cross. You
know, do this. You know, when you, when even though you don't particularly feel like you love
your wife, do a good thing for her at least once a day, you know, and, and if people do those things,
if I do those things, then over time, I discover they're not only easier to do, but the way that
I think I...
about them changes so that conviction actually follows conditioning. The action precedes
the belief. The belief is not, and I was actually, I just, I saw, there's a quote, a great
quote from St. Athanasius. I think it's on the, from the, on the incarnation, which I just
saw today where he says, and I'm probably slightly paraphrasing, but he says, unless you
have a pure mind and try to imitate, you cannot possibly, this is how it is. You cannot
possibly under-
the teachings of the saints,
unless you have a pure mind
and try to imitate their life.
It's one of the best,
I mean, and it's great
because it's one of those quotes
that even if you take it out of context,
it still has the same meaning.
Yeah.
And if you say that,
like if you're not living it,
then you can't understand it.
Yeah.
It's not, it's not possible.
Right?
And so yes, ideas,
these thoughts, these things are epiphenomenal, right?
And this is...
all the time on this show.
Kind of the whole purpose of this show
is correcting a lot of bad ideas and ways of thinking
we've gotten from our culture and our society.
And most of these things aren't things
that someone sat down and told us and we believed.
It's a point.
We were taught these as lessons, right?
And in fact, a lot of them, if we were asked straight out,
like you, if you ask the average Christian straight out
do angels and demons exist.
say, yeah. Yeah. Does that have any effect on anything? They're
let no. Yeah. We're actually doing about that. Right. You know,
six days a week, you live basically the same way an atheist does
and then go to church, right? An atheist who's a reasonably
moral person, right? No, what was taught that, right? And if
asked directly, they wouldn't say they believe it, right? But
Through years of living as
certain way, being in a certain society, having media present you information in a certain
way, right?
We've all of us, hosts of the show included, been guided to certain ways of looking at things
and viewing things.
Slowly over time.
And so we've got to break those, but those ideas, those thoughts, those ways of thinking,
those ways of viewing the world came through practice, came through a way of life, came
through with.
repeated experiences.
And the opposite is true as well.
All the time I have folks who come from, for example,
who come into the Orthodox Church
from a Protestant background,
and we're getting near the end of their cataclysis
and they're kind of concerned because,
oh, I'm supposed to get chrysmate
and I'm supposed to get baptized.
And I'm still not sure about this merry stuff.
right still makes me a little I don't know right because of the way they were brought up and my
answer to them is like well then no gatekeeping you cannot be critter about until you agree with
this list of points of theology from the Orthodox Church right tell the exact opposite tell
them that's fine right we'll baptize you will Chris make you live as an Orthodox Christian and
invariably within a couple of years, those people...
say, Oh, yeah, son, I get it. Right? I never got it, but I came to the acathesims and now
this they are, they're toko stuff makes sense to me all of a sudden. Right? Now iconography
makes sense to me all of a sudden. Right? That's, that's the answer. Right? The answer is
life. Right? The answer is not having an argument where I prevail and demonstrate that
at this point of theology is correct.
I kind of wish it was that because I'm good at it, but that's not how it works.
I much better at intellectual argument than I am at life, right?
I mean, I've got a wall of graduate degrees to attest to this, right?
And non-Sainthood to test to the other.
But that's the reality of how it is.
And you know, St. Paul.
So again, St. Paul and Romans.
it up, right? It's the not the
hearers of the law, but the
doers who are justified. Pretty
straightforward. You can know
Torah, backwards and forwards.
It doesn't help you if you don't
do it. All right, well, that's
the end of the second half, but
there is a third half to come. So,
we're going to take our final
break and it will be right back
with the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and
Father Stephen DeYoung will be
back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the
Lord of Spirits. Give them a
at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-A-F-P-R-D-O.
Introducing a new book from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Healing Work.
Giving humanity a second chance.
Written by Joshua McCool.
Healing Work is essentially a how-to guide
to help readers locate the starting point
in their own healing process.
gain confidence in responding to the ebbs and flows, successes and setbacks of the healing
journey.
This book is about helping people learn how to make their healing journey shorter.
It's tragic that so many get stuck in distressing emotional patterns for years or even decades.
Often because they simply don't know how to identify why they're suffering.
We can work to reduce unnecessary emotional suffering by learning to identify what we
need to focus on and by developing skills to now
the emotional space between the extremes of anger and happiness.
Healing work, giving humanity a second chance.
Available now at store.angentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat 5-5-8-F-3.
video.
And we're back with the third half of the Lord of Spheres in this pre-recorded episode.
So again, we're not taking calls this time because Father Stephen is up in Canedia when
this air is live.
Great white North, eh?
That's right.
Where everyone's sorry.
Yeah, so we're talking about judgment.
We're talking about Doomsday.
And we just spent the first couple of halves talking about, well, especially this last
half works, and the judgment according to works, but also the day of the Lord and the
first half in particular and what exactly that means.
Judgment day.
Yeah.
End of days.
Which you won't know what I'm about to talk about, but it's a weird fact that you should,
you really think about it, like especially Dominic Mysterio.
I mean, I get what he's doing, but it's a weird faction.
Anyway, go ahead.
I'll look that up later, I guess.
Yeah.
There's a very select group of our audience.
I was gonna say, is that a Terminator thing?
No. Okay.
I know there's a Terminator to Judgment Day,
and I have seen that film.
That's a pro-rasselin thing.
Oh, oh yeah, yeah.
A friend of mine actually worked back,
So one of my friends who was a...
stage end as well, he actually worked a couple of pro wrestling shows and had some really
fun stories to tell about, you know, guys who the wrestlers like out in the hallways,
they turn the camera on them and they're like all, and you know, something their chest,
whatever, some other guy. And then as soon as the cameras are off, they're, you know, their
buds, you know, yeah. So it might not be real father Steven.
I'm just saying it might not be bad.
There are kids who listen to this show, man.
What's next? Santa Claus?
Well, who are you after next?
John, you are a thief of joy.
I am.
So, all right.
So, but yeah, what does all that have to do with the bodily resurrection?
which probably some people can sound like a
of non-sequitor.
Yeah, it's not like we ramble or digress on this show.
I mean, obviously it must be pertinent.
Not even a little bit.
No, I mean, I think right off the bat,
even though some people might say,
okay, well, the bodily resurrection
and the last judgment, those are different topics.
Like, they're thinking about systematic theology
and theological topics and subheadings, right?
I mean, obviously from any Christian person.
the respect of the resurrection of the body
and the final judgment are linked
at least sort of temporally, right?
Like these sort of things that go together,
they happen together, right?
But what we're gonna talk about here,
we're not talking about the bodily resurrection per se.
We talked about that in previous episode.
But we're talking about why those two things are linked
and how those two things.
the bodily resurrection and the last judgment, the final judgment, the final setting right
of the world by God, right? Restoration of justice by God. How those two things go together.
And ultimately, spoilers for this third half, how they not only go together, but they're inseparable.
So we have to start by talking about sort of the...
The origins, right, we talked about ideas arising.
Once does the concept of the bodily resurrection arise, right?
So if folks know anything about the Pharisees
and the Sadducees, right, we show up in the New Testament.
If you know one thing about Pharisees and Sadducees,
it's that the Pharisees believed
that the bodily resurrection and the Sadducees did not, right?
That's kind of the thing people know.
Yes, and then the corny joke is that's why they were sad you see right?
I know I know I grew up with that joke. I did I grew up with that joke
You should never joke about the Pharisees of the Sadducees
I got a very angry phone call about this once
Well from a Pharisee or Sadducee not joking that is not a job
I really did get a phone call excoriating me for joking about the Pharisees of the Sadducees
It's from a Southern gentleman who is very upset.
So, and so this is true.
This is not, you know, the one thing you thought
you knew about Pharisees, it's had you sees is wrong.
The one thing you know about Pharisees, it's had you sees
is right.
That is correct.
Yes, right.
Now, it may not be for the reason you think, right?
Because if there's two things people know
about the Pharisees and the Sadducees,
the second thing that
know is that the Sadducees only considered the Torah, the Pentateuch, the five books of Moses,
only considered that to be canonical and nothing else, whereas the Pharisees had like the larger
Hebrew Bible. They included the prophets and depending on when we're talking about in history
a bunch of the writings, right?
Those were formed over time, right?
And even in the first-
there were still debates about like Esther and Ecclesiastes and some of those.
But, and so because that's the second thing people know, people tend to assume that
the second thing they know and the first thing they know are directly related.
And this happens through a kind of anachronistic belief
that first century...
Jewish folks believed in Soluscriptura. Yeah. And therefore, well, since the bodily resurrection
isn't clearly described in the Torah itself, therefore the Sadducees didn't believe in it,
because it wasn't in their Bible, whereas the Pharisees had the bigger Bible. And so it was in
in there. So they believed in it, right?
And that's wildly anacridistic, because first of all, nobody have a Bible.
What's a Bible?
It's the way we use it.
Yeah.
So these are separate scrolls and stuff, right?
This is a question of the relative authority of books, right?
But also the Pharisees of the Sadducees.
actually agreed that the Torah was in a class by itself. The Pharisees did not
and their descendants in rabbinical Judaism do not put the other texts in the
Hebrew scriptures. Right? The Navi-Emen, the Ketuvim, the prophets and the
do not put them on the same level as the Torah.
So, that's not the real source of disagreement there about the text.
Both of them agreed, right?
The issue was primarily a liturgical issue in that the way this functionally happened,
we've talked before about how even in Christian terms what makes something canonical is that
it's read publicly in the gathering.
Right.
And this is derived from
this with the Pharisees as Adjezis, the Pharisees had a reading from these other texts in addition
to the Torah reading in the structure of the synagogue service, which to the Sadducees
looked like they were putting them on par with the Torah. The Pharisees insisted otherwise.
And they did just insist otherwise in arguments.
This is played out in the synagogue service, right?
There's the procession with the Torah scroll.
There's, right, the Torah reading is treated differently
than the other readings, right?
And by the way, the same is true for Christians
in the New Testament.
This is how anachronistic that kind of
Solicitor of you is.
And you can see this in an Orthodox church today,
Right, we make a procession with the gospel book.
The gospel reading is only done by clergy.
The epistle reading can be done by lay people.
In some situations, the epistle reading can be done
by people who aren't even Orthodox Christians
let alone clergy.
People, everyone stands for the gospel reading.
People can sit for the epistle reading.
Right, so...
even this is something we've actually kept from Judaism as the idea of
of preeminence within the canon. And this is not a rabbit trail. I will go down
here, but that also that idea of preeminence within the canon. If you don't
understand that, it's going to make it really hard for you to understand what's
going on in the Orthodox Church when we talk about the preeminence of
of Scripture within tradition.
how that cash is out.
Yeah.
Um, so, um, right, but so that's, this is a, this is a liturgical primarily dispute.
Canon disputes were always liturgical disputes in the ancient church and in, um, in ancient
Judaism.
Um, so that's not why.
Right.
Essentially, he's didn't believe it in the Pharisees did.
Um, it is true.
It is true that the places where we explicitly see the bodily resurrection discussed in the Hebrew Bible are from later texts, texts later than the Torah, right?
Written after the Torah.
So that much is true, right?
That much is true.
But for the Pharisees, the bodily resurrection is not so much derived from these...
places where it's mentioned in these other texts, as these other texts are reflecting the belief in the bodily resurrection that developed because the bodily resurrection, right, this idea, this idea of the bodily resurrection,
emerged from and played a particular role within the understanding of God's justice,
which is why we're talking about it now.
why it's critically important to understanding the last judgment, the final establishment
of justice.
So we're going to read one of these texts.
It's a little long.
You'll live.
But this is from Job.
And this is one of the clearest texts.
And then we'll have a couple of other shorter texts from the Old Testament for the Hebrew
Bible.
the talk.
very specifically, very clearly about unambiguously
about the bodily resurrection.
These three texts we're going to read from the Hebrew Bible
are actually probably clearer in terms of the physical
bodily resurrection than a lot of the texts
in the New Testament are.
Right, like that's how clear it is.
All right, Job chapter 19 verses 1 through 27.
Then Job answered and said,
how long will you torment me and break me in pieces
pieces with words.
you have cast reproach upon me. Are you not ashamed to wrong me? And even if it be true that I have
aired, my error remains with myself. If indeed you magnify yourselves against me and make my
discretion argument against me, know then that God has put me in the wrong and closed his net about me.
Behold, I cry out violence, but I am not answered. I call for help, but there is no justice.
He has walled up my way so that I cannot pass, and he has set, set darkness upon my paths.
He is strict from me, my glory.
and taken the crown from my head.
He breaks me down on every side and I am gone
and my hope has he pulled up like a tree.
He has kindled his wrath against me
and counts me as his adversary.
His troops come on together,
they have cast up their seed ramp against me
and encamp around my tent.
He has put my brothers far from me
and those who knew me are wholly estranged from me.
My relatives have failed me,
my close friends have forgotten me.
The guests in my house and my maid servants
count me as a stranger,
I've become a foreigner in their eyes.
I call to my servant, but he gives me no answer.
I must plead with him with my mouth for mercy.
My breath is strange to my wife, and I am
a stench to the children of my own mother.
Even young children despise me when I rise,
they talk against me.
All my intimate friends appore me, and those who my love
have turned against me.
My bones stick to my skin and to my flesh,
and I've escaped by the skin of my teeth.
Have mercy on me, have mercy on me, oh you, my friends,
for the hand of God has touched me.
Why do you like God?
me, why are you not satisfied with my flesh?
O, that my words were written, O, that they were inscribed in a book, O, that with an iron
pen and lead they were engraved in the rock forever.
For I know that my Redeemer lives, and at the last he will stand upon the earth.
And after my skin has been thus destroyed, yet in my flesh I shall see God, whom I shall
see for myself, and my eyes shall be hold, and not another besides me.
my heart.
feints within me. Right. So you may say, why did we read all that since the stuff about the bodily
resurrection is right there at the end? Yeah. Because it's important to see how it's framed.
Right. So I don't know of a more clear statement than after my skin has been thus destroyed yet in my
I shall see God in my flash.
I am not another word.
Right?
Yeah.
So.
uh this is right I know there'll be some people who will point out right well like the Greek tradition
identifies Job as being the grandson of Esau which is true uh and they'll say well this takes
place the patriarchal period this is true it was not written before the Torah.
Job didn't write it text doesn't say Job wrote it and I don't care if a study Bible notes as
show brought it.
he didn't write it. Okay. That's that. I don't know where the story by Will do is even
getting that. So you can look at it in Hebrew. It's it was it was written after the Torah.
Okay. And also now that that has ticked a certain group of people off, let me take off another
group of people that really clear statement of the bodily resurrection we just read. The
Greek butcherset.
the Greek absolutely butchers it like changes verb tenses and stuff. And there's no way to determine why we don't know who translated Greek Job because again as I know we've mentioned on the show before the step to agent the work of the 70 rabbis was a translation of the Torah of the Pentateuch.
They didn't translate Job.
Letter to Aristos does not say they translated Job.
None of the church fathers say they translate.
in joke. So we don't know who translated it. Maybe it was a sadgesy that he was deliberately
thinly with it, right? Who knows? But yeah, it gets made hash in Greek and the Hebrew
is very clearly talking about the bodily resurrection. It's very clearly talking about the
the fact that God will stand upon the earth on the last day.
In verse 25, in the Hebrew, not so clear in the Greek, right? That may be another reason why it got
fiddled with. So yeah, I hate to break it to people, but not all of the differences between the
Greek and the masoretic text make the Greek more Christian. There's a few that make it less Christian.
So now that I've alienated a whole other group of people, sorry, it's just true.
The point of reading all that is, right, in the setting,
Joe is your responding to one of his quote unquote friends.
Yeah.
Who have been hitting him with the no God wouldn't be doing this to you unless you were a
sinner.
Repent of your wickedness, you wicked man.
Yes, right.
Which, you know, to use our language from the first half, they are mistaking pruning for,
you know, the whole wheat and tears.
Be cut off.
Yeah, be cut off.
So, right? And so, this is the, and so he's saying, look, no. And so his expression here of the bodily resurrection, right, is Job saying what he's saying here is, even if I don't get justice in this life,
Even if my righteousness is not vindicated in this life, right?
I know that the day will come.
When I will stand in my body, me, not somebody else, not my descendant, whatever, but me,
I will stand before God, right?
And on that day, I will have my justice.
I will have my vindication.
That's what he's saying here.
Because I'm a righteous man and I have suffered horribly, right?
But I know that that
Ultimately, God will bring forth justice even if it's someday long after I'm dead. He will bring me back to life
And I'll say before him and he will give justice right
And so all that framing and all that reading was
That we have to get this dynamic. This is what the bodily resurrection is about the bodily resurrection is about justice
Because in this world a whole lot of righteous people go to their death in suffering in misery
Right? Exhibit a martyrs. Right? Right?
Diahorable death. Sometimes they die young. Right?
And on the other side in this world there are wicked people who perceive to prosper their
whole lives and go to their deaths and leave all their wealth to their children.
And we can look at that, not out of resentment or envy or jealousy.
can look at
that based on what God has told us in the scriptures and say that is unjust. That is not the way God created things to be.
Right? And so there are folks out there who look at that and say, that's not how the Bible says God created things to be. Therefore God must not exist.
Right. Right.
Yeah, but that's not the route Job takes.
Yeah, that's not the same stake.
The route, the same stake is, therefore, God will bring justice to this in the future.
When that final justice happens, right, when the last judgment happens and justice is
finally established, then there will be justice for this.
And that requires that all of us, the righteous, the wicked, everybody, that we're all alive
again in our bodies it's us not somebody else standing on this earth.
in front of him to receive that justice.
One way or the other.
Right?
So you see this again, another place where
the bodily resurrection is very clearly discussed,
is in Isaiah and it's framed in a similar context.
Yeah.
So Isaiah chapter 26, verses 16 through 21,
O Lord, in distress they sought you.
They poured out a whisper.
prayer when your discipline was upon them. Like a pregnant woman who rides and cries out in her
pangs when she is near to giving birth so were we because of you, O Lord, we were pregnant, we
ride, but we have given birth to wind. We have accomplished no deliverance in the earth and the
inhabitants of the world have not fallen. Your dead shall live, their bodies shall rise. You who
dwell in the dust awake and sing for joy, for your dew is a dew of light, and the earth will give
birth to the dead.
Come, my people, enter your chambers and shut your doors behind you.
Hide yourselves for a little while until the fury has passed by.
For behold, the Lord is coming out from His place to punish the inhabitants of the earth
for their iniquity, and the earth will disclose the blood shed on it and will no more cover
its slain.
So yeah, you don't get much clearer than your dead shall live, their bodies shall rise.
Yeah.
explicitly about the bodies.
and the earth will give birth to that, right?
This is as clear as it gets, right?
At least as clear as any statement in the New Testament.
But notice the framework, right?
Especially that last verse.
The earth is gonna disclose the blood shed on it
and no longer cover this lane.
Think of Canaanable, right?
The blood of the martyrs that cries out from the ground, right?
To God, for justice, right?
So here what is the
purpose of the dead being returned to life, justice. Right? This is a little more
negative than jokes. Job was in a positive sense, right? That job would be
vindicated. Right? This is kind of in a negative sense. These these evil doers,
these wicked who have shed this blood will will face the consequences of their
actions. But that also implies the vindication of Israel. That's who's being
talked about here. Right? The other nations have done evil and have
of oppressed Israel.
Right. And and killed up to an equity killing Israelites, right? And the people of Judah and
there's going to be justice for that. Israel is going to be vindicated over against them.
Right. Same kind of context for the bodily resurrection. And another one we'll do a third one
because as Aristotle said, everything that comes in threes is perfect. There we go.
And Dan, that's where there's three halves to this show.
Oh, yes.
Finally, finally we revealed it after almost three years.
Daniel, chapter 12 verses 1 through 3,
at that time, shall arise Michael, the great prince who has charge of your people.
And there should be a time of trouble such as never has been since there was a nation till that time.
But at that time, your people shall be delivered.
Everyone whose name shall be found written in the book.
And many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake,
some to everlasting life and some
to shame and everlasting contempt.
And those who are wise, so shine like the brightness
of the sky above, and those who turn
many to righteousness like the stars forever and ever.
Yes.
So notice there, we again have those who
sleep in the dust of the earth, shall awake, right?
Some to life, some to everlasting life,
some to everlasting contempt, same adjective.
which is almost exactly what Jesus says in.
Yes, yeah.
Right.
But then notice also, notice also, that verse three,
which is one of the classic descriptions of theosis,
that the righteous will shine like the stars of heaven.
Right?
This idea of theosis of the stars placed in the angels who fell.
that whole idea of theosis is not in any way opposed.
the bodily resurrection. No, yeah. Right? Like these are right after each other, these go together,
right? They go together just fine. But again, here, the resurrection of the dead is related to
the last judgment. It's part and parcel of it. So the idea of the bodily resurrection arises from
people have they come to know God.
having come to know what justice is by being taught by God what justice is. Right. And so this
body of the bodily resurrection naturally arises and that's why we see it start showing up in
these later texts. Right. God created us. Right. And he created us not as floating spheres.
Sorry, origin.
He created us, he created us with material bodies, right?
He created, and we are part of his creation
in our material bodies, right?
And so restoring that creation,
transfiguring and transforming that creation
requires us being put back into the proper set
of ordered relationships within ourselves,
with each other, with the rest of the creation.
Hence bodily
resurrection, right, for justice to be restored. This also though is important because the bodily
resurrection and the key element here and the text in Job, another reason why we read the whole
thing, right, really gets at this when he says, I and not another, right? Because there's a lot of ways
in which God's justice is spoken of by people who don't necessarily believe in the bodily resurrection.
Right. And I don't know how much people have heard these because I know we all have siloed
listening and viewing. So I don't know how many people have heard these kinds of things.
But right, the idea that the arc of history bends toward justice. That's actually a quote
from somebody you've heard of. But that's the arc of history bends toward justice. That's
especially Martin Luther King Jr.
That that
justice is sort of this overarching on the whole kind of thing. Right? So there may not
be any justice for, hey, let's just stay where we were. So the people who Dr. Martin Luther King
Jr. said that too. Right. They may not receive justice for their suffering, but ultimately in
the future, their descendants will live in a more just world.
Yeah.
I just looked this up.
I mean, the more exact quote is he says, the arc of the moral universe is long, but it
bends towards justice.
So yeah, it's like it's just a guy, which are saying that things are not great now,
but ultimately it's headed in a better direction.
Right.
But those people are not going to those individual human persons who are standing there
listening to him.
go to their deaths and
suffering and never experience any justice.
Right.
And so people will talk about justice being, you know,
or even from folks who at least tacitly believe in
the bodily resurrection, because it wouldn't be an episode
of Lord of Spirits without at least one sorry, Calvinist,
You know that in eternity
right in the age to come, we'll look back at history and we'll see how everything was perfectly just.
Like retrospectively. That we'll see that nothing needs to get fixed because everything that happened
was perfectly just. Not that things will be fixed in the future. You know, this kind of view that
that justice is a thing about the whole.
Right. But what we see in Job is that that's not the kind of justice we're talking about when we're talking about the bodily resurrection. Right.
Job is emphasizing, no, him, Job. Right. He needed to be vindicated, not his descendants. Right.
not like, you know, after Job was dead, his friends would be like, yeah, Job was
right and we were wrong and finally...
admitted put a little plaque on his grave admitting they were wrong, right? That's not what
we're talking about. Right. It's not even that Job would be a saint in heaven. It's not
even right, someone to make icons or statues of Job or something. Right. And that's some
kind of indication. Right. Job is clear that justice he has personally in his body experienced
this suffer.
He is also going to personally in his body receive
indication and justice for what he's been through.
So God's justice is for each person,
not just for the sweep of history.
Right.
So this idea of resurrection,
Resurrection, follow-the-resurrection as justice.
Right? As part and parcel of the final judgment, the final establishment of justice, forms the basis
for how the apostles, it's not the entirety, but it forms the basis for how the apostles
start to understand the resurrection of Christ.
And that is really clear when we read the New Testament closely.
Right.
that there's an idea that Christ is being vindicated.
Yeah, I mean, some of those early epistolic sermons, you know, this Jesus whom you crucified,
God has raised from the dead and made Lord in Christ.
Right.
You put the righteous one.
Yeah.
The righteous one, St. Peter says at one point, who you crucified.
Right.
That he was righteous and you gave him injustice and God has given him injustice.
God has vindicated him by raising him from the dead.
Right.
And so
So there is this language of justice and justification linked for this reason with resurrection,
with bodily resurrection in the New Testament.
And people have gotten confused by this, especially for the past few hundred years, right,
into taking that language.
which is fairisay language.
This is the language of fairisay Judaism
regarding the bodily resurrection, right?
Taking that language related to justice
and justification and resurrection
and turning and morphing that into
what ultimately treating it as judicial language
and judicial language,
particularly related.
to a retributive justice, criminal justice.
And this culminates in the reformed idea
of Penal Substitutionary Atonement.
But this is a fundamental misreading of the fairisake language
that St. Paul is using, for example,
when he talks about Christ's death and resurrection.
The St. Paul is, remember, a fairisake.
You're a first to himself.
as a Pharisee in the present tense in his letters.
Right.
Um, and this, so this undergirds is thinking.
Right. And so to give an example of this, to give an example of what I'm talking about,
we're going right for it.
We're going to second Corinthians 521.
Yeah. This is, right.
route. This is if if you ever have someone throw you a proof.
text about Piedel's substitute share atonement, there's about a 33 and a third percent chance
it's this one.
Yeah.
That I'm not doing Scott Steiner, Matt.
This is just right.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
So second Corinthians 521, which this is, I mean, even if you don't have like a big ideological
horse in this race, this is a hard verse to understand, especially the way it gets
turnsided in English.
for our sake, he made him to be sin, who knew no sin,
so that in him we might become the righteousness of God.
So the him of course is Jesus.
Yeah.
He made Jesus to sin.
Well, some of the, so he would be God the Father.
The Father, him would be Christ.
Right.
Yeah.
So yeah.
So um
This, of course, yeah, gets puzzled over, right?
Typically, in Protestant and especially reformed contexts, right?
Which is why this, sometimes gets used as a proof text for Petyl substitution.
This idea that, as it's translated usually in English, that God made Christ to be sin is
understood to mean that refer to
all of our sins being sort of put on Christ and then punished there. Right. Which I
think even those folks have to admit is reading a bit in even to the single
translation, right. But here's the real problem, right. And hey guys, here comes
are second, patristic citation for the
episode on the most non-petristic orthodox show on the
show. Um, so Cyril Alexandria is helpful here if you didn't
already know this, right? Cause to kind of figure out what's
going on with this verse, you kind of need to know Hebrew. But
if you don't know any Hebrew, St. Cyril can help you out here.
Right? Because St. Cyril Alexandria points out that what
this means what it says he made him to be.
sin is he says it means he made him to be a sin offering. So if you don't know any Hebrew,
you might look at that and be like, where is Saint Cyril getting that? But if you know
at least a little Hebrew, then you know that in the Torah, the word for sin offering is
just the word for sin.
Does that work?
So if you translated
it wouldn't lead literally the stuff about the sin offerings in Leviticus, it would say,
you know, he will offer a ram as a sin to the Lord. Right? Now, that makes no sense in English.
Would be like, he offers the ram as a sin. Yeah. Right. Wait. What? I thought he was
supposed to do this, right? And that's why we put in the word offering. Because it doesn't
makes sense otherwise. Right? And that's.
sense of it, right? Well, the same thing is true here, but new testament scholars and
Bible translators aren't old testament scholars and Bible translators, so they don't talk.
So that's what St. Cyril's pointing out here, right? Is that St. Paul is just using the
common convention of using that word to mean us in offering? Right? Because St. Paul was
Jewish.
So what this is saying is that God made Christ even though he knew no sin, even though he
was sinless, he made him to be a sin offering, and it's not even even though because he was
sinless, God made him to be a sin offering so that in him we might become the righteousness
of God.
So what is this referring to?
When Saint Paul refers to Christ's death every time, right?
He's not just referring to his death in general.
He's always referring to his crucifixion.
Remember, I preach nothing but Christ and him crucified.
Right.
Crucifixion, crucifixion, the cross, right?
Crucifixion.
We've been crucified with Christ.
Not just we died with Christ.
It emphasizes this over and over again,
because the way Christ died is not irrelevant.
Crucifixion is the death of a condemned criminal.
You
a mode of death that is under a curse according to the Torah.
Cursed is everything that hangs out of tree.
And so Christ is dying the death of a criminal, even though, as St. Paul is pointing out here,
he committed no sin.
about in the Gospels, the thieves. Right?
What is the wise thief, Saint Dismissé?
We are suffering the same fate he is, and we justly.
There's that justice word.
Right? They were being executed for their crimes.
They were dying for their own sins.
Right? They were dying because, as a result of,
their crimes.
Christ was not.
And therefore,
Because Christ's death was unjust, because he was seamless, but was dying as a condemned person,
St. Paul is saying, God could receive it as a sin offering.
Could receive his life, could receive Christ's offering of his life as a sin offering.
And this is grounded in the theology of martyrdom that had developed
within Judaism up to this point, right? We see an example of this in Second Macabees.
Second Macabees is the Macabeean murders are going to their death, right? I believe it is actually
Eliezer who prays and explicitly asks God that he would receive their deaths, right? They're
being murdered by the Seljukids, by the Greeks. The Greek pagan oppressors are murdering them
for their refusal to violate the Torah.
They're refusal to violate God's law.
They're being murdered.
And I believe it's Eliezer who prays out of them that their deaths would be received
by God as sin offerings for the people because they were being killed for righteousness sake,
but the people had committed sins and needed a sin offering.
This is not to say that Christ's death is the same thing.
I'm a Christian, right?
But Christ's death is that pattern,
that already established pattern within the scriptures,
Christ is the sin-quanon
because Christ is not just a righteous Israelite.
Jesus of Nazareth is not just a righteous Israelite.
Jesus of Nazareth is the Messiah.
Jesus, the Nazareth is...
is the word of God, second person of the Holy Trinity.
Jesus is God.
And for his self offering is the ultimate,
the sinquanon, the fulfillment, the filling
to overflowing of that pattern.
But that pattern exists and that pattern
is in the scriptures before Christ's death
for this reason, to enable the understanding
who guys are doing and St Paul's interpreter.
this for us because he has this fair say, understanding of the bodily resurrection.
So Christ is the synchronic of this. He's received as a sin offering and in his resurrection
is the demonstration of his righteousness. Is his vindication as the righteous one, as the just one?
He rises from the dead because of that.
And if you go back a few verses from 2nd Corinthians 5.
21, and see what the context in which St. Paul makes this point.
Verse 14 and 15, he says, for the love of Christ controls us because we have concluded this, that one has died for all, therefore all have died.
And if he died for all that those who live might no longer live for themselves, but for him who for their sake died and was raised.
So...
Those who follow Christ, right, and he's going to get more specific about this in some
other places that we're about to talk about, but have died and risen with him, right?
And that having died and risen with him, right, they now live not for themselves, but for
Christ sick. They now live faithfully.
faithfully to Christ. This is what's met by becoming the righteousness of God.
They might become righteous. For 17, again, in the same context, this is where St. Paul says
therefore if anyone is in Christ he is in new creation. The old has passed away, behold
the new has come. Right? What is new creation?
put in order again. That's what creating is, remember? Yeah. Yeah. Right. It's not that, right?
The person we were like we literally crumbled into dust and we're literally resurrected. That'll
happen later. Right. But we haven't put it back in art. We are already a new creation reordered, justified.
And it's for this reason, right?
I'm sure most of you are reading that this idea of us dying with Christ and rising with Christ,
becoming a new creation. This of course is associated by St. Paul with baptism.
Directly associated with baptism. That we die with Christ and baptism. We rise out of the water,
out of the waters of chaos, a new creation, justified, sanctified, washed as we say in the author
the actual expatismal service.
And as a new...
creation put back in order. And so this is why in Romans 4, verse 25, St. Paul can say that
Christ was delivered for our trespasses and raised for our justification. It was raised for
our justification. The resurrection is towards our being made righteous. Yes. We can put back
in order being justified, yeah, as a new creation. And this isn't just...
Right. So that's taking a key text from St. Paul and showing this. Right. But this is
everywhere in sort of the or layer of the apostolic preaching. So the earliest will read
one of these and then give you references for some more, right. These early sermons by
St. Peter in the book of Acts and the Acts of the Apostles. But a good example of this
is in Acts chapter 2.
Yeah, where he says, God raised him up, referring to Jesus,
losing the pangs of death because it was not possible for him to be held by it.
For David says, concerning him, I saw the Lord always before me, for he is at my right hand,
that I may not be shaken. Therefore, my heart was glad and my tongue rejoiced. My flesh also will dwell
in hope. For you will not abandon my soul to hate ease or let your holy ones seek corruption.
You have made known to me the
of life, you will make me full of gladness with your presence.
Right? So why was Christ raised, according to this quotation,
let's say, Peter uses, because he was righteous, because he was holy.
Right? Therefore he could not remain in the grave.
He hates you, he has no claim on him.
And so he is raised and vindicated.
and you can check out Acts 3, verses 14 and 15, Acts 4, verses 10 and 11,
Acts 5, verses 30 and 31, over and over again, right? Christ is righteous. You
crucified Him. You executed Him as a criminal. God raised Him up and
vindicated him. So we can say that any Christian who's been baptized.
As we say in the Orthodox baptismal service, it has been justified.
We could say that they're already resurrected in one baptismal sense.
In the baptismal sense, they're already, because they've already died to sin.
They've already been made alive in Christ.
But in another sense, we as Christians are awaiting
our final vindication, which will come at the bodily resurrection and will come at the last judgment.
So if we live in this world with all of its suffering, with all of its difficulty,
a life here in this world that inevitably for every one of us ends in physical death.
Right? If we live that faithfully, if we live that righteously, if we live that justly,
Bye.
which we can only do, as we said, through the works of God,
and through repentance. You don't become righteous by never sinning.
You become righteous by repenting when you sin.
If we live our life in that way, then when we stand before the
dreaded judgment seat of Christ, that will be the moment of our vindication.
And if we
don't live in that way, there is the potential for that to end up being our condemnation,
because that sense in baptism in which we're resurrected, that sense in which we're justified
in baptism is not inalienable.
God can begin the work of, of, this is inverting what of St. Paul's examples, but God
Thank you.
can begin the work of putting us back in order and we can abandon that work and go back
to disorder and chaos and destroy what he's been trying to build.
St. Paul uses the opposite example.
He says, talks about, you know, if I rebuild what I once tore down, like tearing down the
edifice of sin and then he goes back and rebuild it.
But it's the same purpose.
We can move away from that.
So it's...
got you get baptized, hey, you're justifying you're in, right?
That's it.
You're resurrected.
Just wait.
You'll be vindicated, right?
And we've been told that we've seen over and over again.
Pretty much every quote we've read from the New Testament.
So that has said that.
Yeah.
Has said because this is true,
therefore now you need to live a life pleasing to God.
Because this is true you need to live.
for yourself but for Christ. Because this is true, you need to walk before God in Me, right?
But it is true. But because it is true, now there is something we need to do.
Not just we need to believe really hard that it's true, but there's something we need to do.
Well, as we wrap up this...
the episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm not going to play the jingle,
but I wanted to do a little etymology.
It seemed weird to play the jingle here at the end.
But yeah, the word doom, titled this episode, Doomsday.
In English, we tend to think of doom as,
I mean, this is the way it's used in the modern sense now,
typically is that doom means a bad outcome.
You know, you're doomed, right? Which is it's kind of funny week even put it that way you're doomed, right?
You know something terrible is gonna happen to you. But the older sense of Doomsday is it was a
synonym for judgment day. In fact, it's the older English word.
And one of the first places that this word comes up or probably more the most well-known early
instances.
is of a book that was called The Doomsday Book,
although usually spelled D-O-M-E-S-D-A-Y,
Doma Stey, because that's the sort of
the early Middle English spelling of it.
And so The Doomsday Book, or Doomsday Book,
was a late 11th century book that was created
at the behest of, well, he's known to history usually,
it's William the Conqueror, but various other epithets
that's retouched to him.
But he's the Norman that conquers England.
And so he orders that this book be made.
And the book actually is a kind of survey of property
in England.
And part of the point of it was to make sure that all the taxes
that he felt that he was owed were paid to him.
But the point of calling it that was, although it was not
I don't know.
that when it was made.
That was later a name attached to a little bit later,
maybe a century or so later.
And one of the reasons that it was called that was,
it was said that it was as unchangeable as judgment day.
So it was a kind of analogy.
But it was really about taking a trip,
a number of people taking a trip around England
and judging what the lands were, just assessing.
sort of a big assessment, right?
And this gives us that earlier sense of doom.
We still have the related verb,
deem, which usually when we say deem,
we don't mean something, some negative outcome, right?
I can just say, I deem that to be true,
which is, I judge it to be true.
I perceive it to be true.
So doom was simply a judgment
or um
a pronouncement, fate, maybe, as it were.
And of course, the word actually has a much older history.
It comes from our old English heritage
and then proto-Germanic and then all the way back
to Indo-European, proto-Indo-European.
And in that proto-Indo-European route,
it means to place or to put something somewhere.
Right?
this sense.
of order, of putting things in order.
And then when it gets into the early Germanic usage,
it starts at that point to be used as judgment,
to perceive, to assess, to see things as they are,
to make a decision based on that.
And this doesn't disappear.
Like you get, eventually you get the word King Dumb,
and that dumb DOM on the end.
refers to the area or the sphere of influence of the king, the sphere in which he is the one
who renders judgment, in which he is the one who's putting things in proper order.
And so, like I said, we think of this word doom as meaning, you know, misfortune.
And doom's day, the end of the world, lots of bad things happening.
Um, but...
The history of the English word really keeps within it all of these biblical
senses that we've been talking about. That judgment is God putting things in
their proper order, perceiving that they're out of order and putting them in
their proper order. And also, judgment is that that's fear of influence. You know,
his kingdom is truly a kingdom. It has that that's fear of influence. His rule,
his ordering.
in our task as living within the kingdom of God,
it's not some other kind of community,
it's God's kingdom is to participate in that doom,
the doom of God, to do it as well,
to also be deeming, to also be placing things
in their proper order.
Number one ourselves, we do that three pendants.
There's a famous
saying, I think from Mount Athos, you know, if you die before you die, then when you die,
you don't have to die. Which means, put yourself in proper order in this life so that when you
depart this life, when you move into life of the age to come, then God doesn't have to do it to you.
It will have already been done with his help here in this life through repentance.
And so you may notice, you know, even though we started out talking about the end of the world,
where we ultimately ended up was the resurrection.
And that's because when we think about Doomsday,
when we think about Judgment Day,
as Christians, we shouldn't merely fear and tremble.
Although, I mean, that's useful.
Our hymns for the Sunday of the last Judgment
are often focused on that and have always been.
This is something that humanity needs.
It needs that kind of warning language.
I know I do.
But that's not the only thing that we should focus on.
We should also focus on the sense that justice is coming,
that God's justice, God's ordering, God's recreation is coming
and is already breaking through.
And we can participate in it even now,
to put ourselves in order, to put the space around us in order,
to have orderly relationships with the people around us.
And when I see orderly, I don't just...
mean I don't mean formal or regimented or anything like that. I mean that we are living
according to God's order which is an order of love and self-sacrifice and humility. That's
what it means to have a truly orderly relationship from God's point of view. And the more that we
do that, the more that we will become fit for the kingdom of heaven, that we will be living
appropriately according to that doom.
and also that we will attract other people by God's grace to participate in it as well.
Right? And so when we think about doom, when we think about the doom of God and Doomsday,
we don't have to be afraid of it. We don't have to have some sense of horror in response.
But rather, it should be about hope.
It should be about hope because the summary of this is resurrection.
Now, there's a resurrection of life and a resurrection of
demination, of condemnation.
That's what Jesus says.
And of course, he's almost quoting the Old Testament as we
heard earlier.
And so the call is to live according to the works of God, to
live in a way such that when we are judged according to our
works, and we will be judged according to our works, not
According to our opinions...
It's not according to our beliefs, according to our works, that when we are judged that
God will look at us and say, well done, good and faithful servant.
Notice He doesn't say well thought or well believed or well agreed with, well done.
It's about doing.
We live in an era in which it's really easy not to do anything.
I only relatively recently learned the expression touch grass, which means what I understand
understand. You've been spending way too much time on the internet. You need to go out and
connect with the world, the 3D world. I think that that's something that we especially
need to remember in this time and place, this point in history, this culture, that we
will be judged according to what we have done. It's very, very easy to try to have all
the right beliefs and to be really good at...
defining them or arguing for them or whatever.
And it's good to have the right beliefs.
But if we're not doing what will be deemed by God at the end to have been faithful to him,
then it doesn't matter what you believe.
It doesn't matter what you say.
It's what we do that counts in the end.
So let's be faithful. Let's be...
Let's be, uh, doomable in the right and the way that will show us to be among the righteous at the end. Father?
So I know there are like five hoovians out there who are upset that I haven't mentioned the
Doom's Day event going on amongst the licensees.
But I'm not into it, I'm sorry.
time-loaded victorious was good, but this one looks kind of lame. But there, I mentioned it.
So there was a time
when you adhere preachers preach about the last judgment. And sort of the way of life that was
scene as being opposed to the Christian way of life was away.
of life that is sort of pleasure seeking, right? People just going out and
wine women and song and having this wild life chasing after the pleasures of
the flesh. So that was, you know, you could do that or you know, you could be a
good, a good upstanding Christian, right? And then when the last judgment comes,
Right, there's, there's gonna be justice for both.
And now the way society has gone.
on, I don't think most people could identify with that
anymore, right?
I don't think those are the two ways of life that people
see set before them.
In fact, I don't think most people in our current society
really see two different ways of life set before them.
I think at this point in our society, post-COVID, now
everything's demonetized.
host.
alienation and isolation and the internet and everything else. I think we're at
the point now where almost everybody is primarily concerned about how they
feel and this isn't some kind of weird selfish self-centered thing. It's more
just everybody is sick and tired of feeling sick and tired. Everybody's tired
feeling bad.
Everybody's tired of feeling hopeless.
Everybody's tired of feeling like their day-to-day life is meaningless.
Like, I'm going to get up every day and do what I do every day, the same thing, over and over again,
until one of these days I'll kill over dead.
And people are just trying to find some way
Happy to speak.
be too much to grasp, but just not feel bad. Just feel okay. Just feel like there's some
purpose to things, or maybe something might get better at some time in the future.
I think people even approach religion that way now. I think a lot of people who are former
atheists and stuff coming back to religion, a lot of it is sadly, I mean, it's a good
result people coming back to, to especially Christianity, but uh...
Well, out of it is desperation.
A lot of it is just, I need something.
I need something that will make some of this mean something or be worthwhile.
And the problem with that, the problem with that.
And we've gotten there by just being broken down.
But the problem is, we're just seeking to alleviate suffering.
just kind of
seeking to anesthetize ourselves for a little while.
We're just kind of seeking
right in escape.
And not to bring everybody down further.
I don't have already brought everybody down,
but not to bring everybody down further,
but there is no escape.
There's suffering and there's trouble in this life.
There always has been, there always will be.
And it's not always
just meaning it doesn't always make sense. Job suffering didn't make sense to him. It doesn't
always make sense. And we're all going to die eventually on a long enough timeline. We all
end up dead. But so there is something we can do. There's something we can do. There's
something we can do.
that will give meaning, that will give us hope, the hope for vindication,
the hope of Christ's return, the hope of judgment.
And it's not avoid suffering.
It's not anesthetize ourselves from suffering.
It's not carve out a few little moments of joy or beauty amidst all the suffering.
It's not avoiding death for as long as possible in any way possible.
We're going to suffer.
Why not suffer for something?
We're all going to die. Why not die for something?
For someone.
For someone who's worth it.
For someone who's something who means something.
We can't avoid this.
suffering. We can't avoid death, but we can make the suffering we face in this
life and we can make our death meaningful.
And we do that by how we choose to receive it.
What we choose to take away from it.
What we choose to learn from it. I mentioned earlier the Maccabee and Marters.
We're being...
tortured to death because they wouldn't eat pork, tortured to death.
In very graphic ways if you read Second Macabees.
And who prayed to God and said, you know, my death received this as a sacrifice on behalf
of the people because we've sinned.
And so each of us has choices to make as we go through our life in terms of who we're
living for and who we're going to die for and what that's going to mean.
And we could make choices such as, we'll sit at the end of our life, whether it's on
our deathbed or whether it's before the Dredge of the seat of Christ.
look at our life and say, yeah, that was all just a meaningless horrible mess.
That's entirely possible if we choose to live that way.
Or we can live it away where we look back out and say, that was hard.
That was difficult.
That was painful at times.
But it was worth it.
And here's why.
Those things I sacrificed were for something.
for Christ and His kingdom.
that suffering in those sacrifices helped get rid of the garbage in my life.
That was making me so miserable.
That what I went through helped this other person.
Help this other person make the next step in their own life.
So this is...
And this is the choice that's before us.
I can't choose tomorrow whether I'm going to get sick or not.
I can't choose whether I'm going to get stuck somewhere.
I can't choose whether I'm going to be in miserable conditions.
I can't control whether I'm going to get an unexpected check
in the mail or an unexpected bill in the mail.
But I can choose what the purpose of all this is going to be.
I can choose whether it's going to be meaningful or not.
And so hopefully, as we think about the last judgment, as we think about wanting to be on
the side that's going to be vindicated, that takes us back as we saw over and over again
in the new test.
that we went over to how we live our life today,
how we live our life for Christ and not for ourselves,
how we try to live a life pleasing to God,
how we try to do the works of God in the world,
so that ultimately all this stuff that we've gone through
and are going through and will go through
will all be worth it in the end,
in the end.
And not just a horror.
a way.
Well, thank you very much for listening to this episode.
This is our show for today.
If you didn't get through to us live during one of our other live shows, you can still
contact us.
You can email us at LordofSpeedSynctionFate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpeed.
Enjoy us for our live broadcasts, although this one and the next one will be live.
On the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific,
and I have to say I miss DMX because he was going to give it to us.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page and join our discussion group.
We've reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly,
share this so with a friend who we know is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.anxrophate.com, stroke support,
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
He wasn't gonna wait for us to get it on our own.
He was gonna deliver it to us.
Thank you. Good night. And God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
the elders and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000.
In thousands of thousands, seeing with a loud voice worthy is the land that was slain
to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation 5.
Verse 11-12.
Glory to God in the highest and on earth peace good will toward men.
This is Ancient Faith Radio, your Orthodox Internet connection.
Saint Ignatius.
first century bishop of Antioch called the God-bearer is one of the earliest witnesses to the truth of Christ and the nature of the Christian life.
Tradition tells us that as a small child Ignatius was singled out by Jesus himself as an example of the child-like faith all Christians must possess.
In bearing God, Father Andrew Damick recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr.